The final event in the diving pool is the men's 10 meter platform competition.
One of the blue ribbon events of the whole games.
A spectacular combination of artistry, athleticism and sheer courage.
It's a long journey to the medals podium though.
32 divers are in the pool for tonight's preliminary round.
Only 18 will survive to make it into tomorrow morning's semi-final.
The top 12 from there will go forward to tomorrow night to compete for gold.
Expect the atmosphere to hit fever pitch tonight because Great Britain's poster boy, Tom Daly, begins his personal quest for glory, having missed out on a medal in the 10m Cinco competition that he and Peter Waterfield finished just out of the frame in fourth place.
The Brits are in action tonight and they've brought their supporters ever.
But the world's best are all in the line-up here.
Two Olympic champions, two world champions.
The Chinese have dominated in the diving pool again, but Russia's Ilya Zakharov, who won a gold at three metres, as we look at Tom Daley and Peter Waterfield there, they're the ones getting the cheers.
Well, that Russian has proved the Chinese are not completely unbeatable.
Indeed, 10 metres is supposed to be the Chinese team's most vulnerable event, mind you.
They've only won gold in three of the last five Olympic Games.
We'll explain the scoring and some of the more technical aspects as we go along, but the important thing here is just to enjoy a great show.
Steve Robiliotis alongside me looking to do just that as well.
Steve, you spent a lot of these games covering the gymnastics and in many ways is this what these guys are?
They're gymnasts.
Well they are really and you're going to see a lot of the skills from gymnastics transfer across to the 10 metre platform.
They've only got three seconds though to get it done from platform to water or even a little less than that and six dives each in what is quite a lengthy session for them and as you mentioned
It's a little bit of a marathon effort to get yourself from these preliminaries into the final.
So they don't want to start poorly.
In that respect it's also like the gymnastics.
You have a major qualifying day which allows you to progress to a number of other events.
In this case it's the
platform on through to the semi-final to the final and we wish them all well and we wish them safe competition because that is a long way up and some of the competitors will tell you themselves they don't know why they do it and they're very aware of the danger but it also makes for spectacular sport.
They hit the water at speeds in excess of 30 miles per hour, so get it wrong.
And getting it wrong is the big pressure, of course, Steve, because, again, like the gymnasts and one or two of these artistic sports, that you cannot afford to get a dive wrong, because it could be game over.
And with your first dive, there's always that pressure, no matter how experienced you might be, and Gleb Galperin will go up first, the 27-year-old Russian, and he's seen it all, done it all, been out for a spell with injuries like many of them have.
But to be the very first competitor up brings its own pressure, but it won't be unfamiliar to most of these lads who come to this level of competition only because they're very, very good.
Six dives each tonight.
Each dive has an agreed degree of difficulty.
Seven judges who mark each dive out of 10.
The highest and lowest two marks are discounted.
Then the remaining total is multiplied by the degree of difficulty or the tariff that is given to each dive.
Sounds complicated.
The captions you'll see come out.
The graphics there will make it very clear which marks are counting.
So don't worry too much about any technicalities.
Just enjoy the show, as we've said, because the action here can be spectacular.
11 of these divers plus one more have already been in action in the synchronized swimming which at least gives them a feel of the pool but for most of them it's been a long long wait to get their Olympic Games underway.
Quite a warm evening and we're sitting up towards the top of the venue where the warm air is settling and we are certainly feeling it.
I wouldn't mind a dip in that pool myself but I don't think they're going to let us down there Roger.
Unfortunately not.
You'll see there's just a little bit of a glaze across the top of the pool.
They put a spray on top of it because when the divers are coming down it gets rid of that mirror effect and they can actually judge the distance they are from the water.
I mean it's frightening to think all that is going through their mind.
They tend to pick a spot on the ceiling or the outside to use as a rotation point to orientate themselves around.
For those of us who don't do this sport, we don't know how they do it really.
No, it takes a lot of courage, a serious amount of training and work in the gym and a bit of work between the ears as well to convince yourself how it should be done and that should it be done at all at Gleb Galperin first of all.
One of the most experienced competitors in the competition, the dives will get more difficult as they go along.
Inward three and a half, Somersault with a 3.2 tariff.
And always so pleased to get that first one out of the way.
And it looked like he did a very good job.
In tight to the platform.
That's part of the danger, of course, and hit the water nice and vertically.
And the good score is coming in for him.
And an 88 to start with.
And four scores rejected, as Roger's explained to you, the top two and bottom two.
Nine and nine and a halfs are excellent stuff.
This is Lin Yue, who's one of the two Chinese divers.
He was the 2008 Olympic Synchro champion competing this time individually in with three and a half somersault tucked position.
Just managed to fold it in underneath the water, make that little somersault beneath to try and get those shins vertical.
Nice tight tuck position and gets through those somersaults early so he can spot the water.
20 of nines coming the way of Lin Yue.
And they try and drag those bubbles down with them to create the best possible entry and least possible splash.
You'll see them on the way down, the replays, which I should emphasize, the judges don't see those replays.
We do, you do, but the judges have to get their judgment right in one go.
Victor Ortega from Colombia, his second Olympic Games, and he kicks off for the back two and a half somersault, one and a half twist, piked.
Oh just rolled that one over with his feet and that's a little error that the judges never miss.
Certainly seem to get through the twisting okay.
Spots the water now and those feet just roll over so no chance of nines there.
The judges are looking for that tightness in either the tucked or the pikes position just how close you can get your torso to the thighs and really bunched up there.
So, he's giving up a few points to the early divers already but the chances to make them up, of course, with this long first session.
Anton Zakharov from Ukraine.
Next to go.
Not to be confused with Ilya Zakharov from Russia who won the Syncro competition.
In with
popular starting dive and it gives you a chance at home to compare how well it's performed.
Closeness to the board is just unnerving at times, isn't it?
Yeah, and I don't think he was still a little bent at the hips.
as he entered the water.
So it wasn't quite vertical.
Hadn't quite come out of it.
A little concern there, I think, for how tight he was to the platform.
And seventy-two for Zakharov.
Timofey from Belarus.
Tenth in the World Championships in Shanghai in twenty-eleven as his best performance to date.
point.
and maybe just slightly under rotating as he hit the water as opposed to Ortega who overcooked it a little bit of a loss of leg form there as the ankles came apart so it sounds too like the judges have spotted what we have the ankles just couldn't quite lock themselves together they actually came apart twice so 72
from the Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
Just 16 years of age, there's a lot of teenagers in this competition as well.
Forward three and a half somersault.
Galperin's 88 is still standing at the moment, but we're expecting the Chinese competitors here to do a wonderful job.
So graceful.
And you see that he's absolutely ripped that entry.
There's barely a splash.
This drags all the bubbles down with him.
two eights and an eight and a half there.
This is Jimmy Connor from Australia.
Seventeen years of age from Melbourne.
Lives in Brisbane, trains there.
And he's just rolled the feet over there.
He won't be too pleased with that first effort.
He was the youngest in the Australian team at the Delhi Commonwealth Games.
He was just 15.
He's come to the top quickly and early.
But not perhaps his best opening dive as the sevens come in.
He's entitled to be nervous.
frighteningly young some of these competitors.
Quite an age range right up into the early 30s like Peter Waterfield from Great Britain, one of the more senior divers in the whole competition down to 15 and 16 year old young boys really, Martin Wolfram.
He's age 20 from Germany.
Arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half twists, an ambitious opening dive.
His arm stand positions are really heart in mouth for all of us watching.
High tariff to start off with at 3.6.
See if he can cash in.
Now okay, we consider the degree of difficulty is going to help him, but the execution not perfect.
The lower tariff dives have got to be executed absolutely spot on.
You've got a little bit more margin for error on the higher, more difficult dives, but obviously they want to cash in, don't they?
Yeah, and a different sort of error there.
He wasn't quite square to the water.
His feet were twisted, ankles certainly together.
And that, again, should be an error that the judges can catch at first look, their first and only look.
Jankler Aguera from Cuba, second Olympic Games.
age 22 another forward three and a half somersault well he crashed into the water really that was hardly missable the error is on the entry he's a little bent in the pike position there's a few problems here for him he wasn't square
And it is the errors that the judges are looking for.
We certainly don't mean to sound negative about these great divers.
They're at the Olympics because they're the world's best.
But we're trying to reflect the thoughts of the judges here.
And the 61.5, that's the lowest so far.
So he had a few problems.
Next up is Alexander Bondar from the Ukraine who's already competed in the Syncro competition with Alexander Kovarov finished eighth in with three and a half somersault to begin his routine.
All very tidy.
Should do well here, Bondar.
Not too many
Some of the Eastern European divers are a little bit more powerfully built, which does tend to give a different impression.
They're almost more muscular divers than some of the Chinese divers who are so incredibly slight and whippy through the air, aren't they?
Yes, and there's less mass entering the water.
It gives the Chinese divers a better entry quite often.
But the powerful men can certainly get the job done in a different way.
Jiho Park from Korea.
Just rolling over a little for Park, out of Busan in Korea.
Had a successful Asian Games, third in the Syncro three-meter springboard.
And 72.
Equals seventh best mark.
Going to take a long time for these positions to really make a huge amount of sense with 32 divers to to get through.
Really a question of them getting this evening out the way, making no mistakes, getting a feel for the competition and maybe at the top end laying down the odd marker if you're amongst those with high aspirations.
Victor Minibayev from Russia.
Sixth in the 10 meter synchro as well.
in with three and a half somersault tucked.
Well he was there a long time and I wonder if there were a few stray thoughts entering his mind with the execution
was solid until he kicked out for the entry and he was just caught a bit short.
So that large splash is such a giveaway.
A little bit of a split in the tuck position.
Most of the divers have that.
It doesn't upset the judges too much.
They really only see that from side on.
But Minnibaev has paid a penalty for the entry for sure.
Got to get the right push off as well to get through the rotations in time to unwind to give themselves the chance of the clean entry.
There's no spring on that.
Obviously, it all comes from their own push off and their own technique.
German Sanchez from Mexico.
Silver medalist in the 10 meter synchro.
Mexico who've had a decent games in the diving pool.
Such a strong nation in this sport, Mexico.
Oh nice, the crowd really appreciated that entry there.
They're instant experts like everyone at home but you learn to pick a good dive don't you and the entry is such an important impression to leave.
They call it the rip, don't they?
And you can hear that different sound.
He's only 47km at Seven Stone Six.
He's one of the lightest going and really the spin speed there in his rotations.
And he's earned the top mark so far.
Galperin, the first diver, was leading for quite a time there with 88, but now 89.1 for Jemin Sanchez.
Well, his strong performance in the synchro would certainly have upped his confidence and confidence as in all sports, but this in particular is massive.
And you can understand why from that formidable height.
Riley McCormick from Kamina.
Again, a very nice entry from Riley.
his second Olympics.
He didn't make the final in Beijing, finished 16th so his first aim will be to not just get through tonight but tomorrow morning and be in the final will be good for him.
He'll turn 21 in a couple of weeks and has made a very solid start here.
73.5 leaves him in equal seventh position and now lots of interest about our next competitor.
Yep, one of the stars of the show
The superstar from Beijing, Matthew Mitchum.
He is a big man, isn't he?
Well, he's a big star in Australia, that's for sure.
His face has been all over the pre-Olympic publicity because he's a defending champion.
But I think even Matthew would admit that the entry here wasn't quite what he was looking for.
The ever so tiny over rotation of the feet.
first Australian male to win an Olympic gold medal in diving since 1924 when he got it four years ago in Beijing in the most spectacular fashion with one of the great dives of all time and the last round to snatch victory.
Loves competing, you can see that with a smile.
Armand Hismervik of Norway.
Opening back two and a half somersault with one and a half twists and he got through everything here pretty tidily.
Feet just came together a little tidily but he's going to pick up some nice marks here.
Gizmovic with an 81.6.
Anything in the 80s is going to leave you in good stead for your second dive and onward.
It's German Sanchez, huge first score of 89.1.
Francesco Delomo from Italy.
This is his third Olympic Games.
So, an experienced competitor.
Forward two and a half somersault with one twist, Pite.
Very nice.
Bring lots of experience to bear here.
Ninth in the platform back in Athens, oh four.
Not too much wrong there for Francesco.
Just a confidence building start.
72.5.
We'll need to build on that.
Varying degrees of pedigree in the country's diving history, really.
Divers like Christopher Eskilsson from Sweden don't have a massive tradition in this sport and facilities sometimes more limited.
Back two and a half somersault, one and a half twist for his opening dive.
One of the divers is really looking to get into that semi-final first as a benchmark of progress and achievement.
He's done a nice job here.
Try and get through the twists as early as possible.
Square yourself up for the entry.
And not too much wrong there from Christopher Eskilsson, 23 years old, trains in Malmo.
It just bothered me a little that he wasn't quite square, but 76.8, that's all right.
He's top 10 at the moment.
32 in the field, of course, at this stage.
Eric Sain from Canada.
His first Olympic games.
Had success as a synchro diver but he's on his own with a back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Again, quite a high tariff dive to open up your program with.
Yes, and he didn't quite get through it.
There was a big splash because he wasn't vertical.
A little bend at the hips on entry.
This will show us so much more clearly, the slow mo.
Oh, his knees were bent there.
There were a number of problems there and the judges have hit him hard.
Oh, it was messy.
I'm sorry.
I want to be more complimentary.
But he put the tough one in early, maybe to get it out of the way.
But 59.4 is not too special.
Not in your first Olympic dive.
Brian Nixon Lomas from Malaysia.
Arm stand back double somersault one and a half twist to start his program.
His third Olympic Games.
very nice created a good entry even if he wasn't completely vertical so he's ticked a couple of boxes and maybe left one unchecked but he's a former world junior champion and he created history for malaysia when he achieved that in 2004 and he's going to get some good marks here and with a reasonable tariff he'll be okay
with an eighty-one six.
So, that's good enough for a equal fourth position at the moment.
Next up is Ivan Garcia from Mexico.
Another half of the silver medal winning duo in the ten meters
Opening up the forward four and a half somersault.
Spin speed going on there.
That's a three point seven tariff as well.
Not afraid to put the tough dives in early.
He's got a four point one coming later.
Feet did roll over.
It's a lot of somersaults to get through in time to spot the water and get yourself vertical and square.
But 81.4.
Well, the United States have had a bit of a diving revival in these games with such a huge early tradition in the Olympic Games coming from the States.
Nick McCrory has a bronze to take home in the 10 meter synchro with David Budaya who's to dive in a few minutes but he gets a chance to open his program.
In with three and a half somersaults.
Well, almost zero splash.
Gets a warm round of applause here from the crowd that will be reasonably neutral until the British divers come up.
He can show that bronze medal to his uncle, the British swimmer who in 1976 picked up bronze in the 800 freestyle, Gordon Downey.
Of course, Nick McCrory representing the USA.
At a 76.8, more than respectable.
The announcer just asking the enthusiastic crowd to turn off the flash guns in their camera phones and cameras they brought to record the event.
Pointing out there is quite enough light in here and you don't want to distract the divers.
Jose Guerra from Cuba.
getting on with his dive very sharply indeed forward three and a half somersault a little too quickly perhaps there's the feet just flipped over at the end of this one so get up he'll be penalized for that with six and a halfs and sevens
A shame.
A lot of the other parts of that dive were nice, but that last impression is just vital.
It's a bit, as we compare with gymnastics, it's like sticking the landing for a tough routine.
If you don't get the entry right, the judges are just left with a bad impression.
Sebastian Villa next from Columbia.
Back two and a half somersault, one and a half twist.
That's a three point two degree of difficulty.
Oh, very nice.
He got a bronze medal in the Pan Am Games in the 10 metre platform last year in Guadalajara.
That's a sports festival that's gaining in prestige.
And he's attracting eights.
And that's a top ten dive at the moment.
Still plenty to come.
Next up, one of the big hitters, as we just see those marks confirmed there.
David Budaya from the United States.
Rons in the 10 meter synchro.
Five foot nine, a much bigger build diver.
Some of the five four five fives that we've seen already.
Arm stand back double somersault, two and a half twists, three point six and opening the show with a big number.
Well, okay, I'd be glad it's got a big tariff because there were a couple of small problems there.
Done well, this was a dive that had the chance to be up there in the top three, but you just observe the bigger splash there.
He likes the difficult dives.
He chose the highest degree of difficulty in the finals in 2008 in this event and finished 10th.
So he likes to challenge himself, obviously.
First US diver to have scored 600-plus points under the current scoring system.
And the dyer, eighth.
Now, here's the star, possibly the favorite Kubo from China, the world champion.
In with three and a half somersault to put down his first marker.
His teammate Lin is sitting in third position.
Always very tidy.
Oh, the judges like it.
It's frighteningly close to the platform.
Very vertical position, slightly bigger splash than perhaps he likes.
But into third.
Some of the big hitters have ended up down the bottom end of this in the in the draw for the dive order.
They'll be seeded after tonight of course.
This is Sasha Klein from Germany.
Twice European champion at ten meters in with three and a half somersault to begin.
We've seen a few of these dives in this first series and none too much better than this one from Sacha Klein.
Very tidy, very clean on entry.
Twenty-six years of age.
Very experienced.
Eight golds and two silvers at European Championship level but this of course is very much a level up but good opening.
Eighty-one point six a popular score in this first series and four other four divers that on that score.
Vadim Kaptur from Belarus.
Another one of the
He did have a head injury last year in June when he hit the platform while training with his partner Timofey Hordachev.
But this is a beautiful dive.
Takes some courage to come back, but where's the splash?
He couldn't make one.
And the 72.
The difficulty just down a little.
That's why he's not up in the high 70s.
The crowd, as you can hear, already cheering because
up on the board is the great home hero Tom Daly from Great Britain one of the poster boys of the whole London 2012 Olympic Games still only 18 years of age his second Olympics so much expectation on Tom Daly back two and a half somersault two and a half twists and that's a 3.6 to start with
I would like him to have done better so that the crowd had a bit more to influence the judges with but you saw the splash over it came.
He's so clean through the air but just let it go at the end and the splash won't convince the judges that this was a dive that was in control.
Finished fourth in the 10 meter synchro, doing brilliantly in the first three dives and then they got the fourth one wrong and it cost them dearly, cost them a medal.
He just has to settle down and make sure he qualifies and look to build through his through his campaign.
He's not going to win it tonight, but you can lose it.
It's not a disastrous start, but it's not a confidence building one either.
Chiarabini from Italy.
in with three-and-a-half somersault.
Yep, well there's youth perhaps exposed with his opening dive there, his hips a little bent on entry and the splash, a little size, well he got through
Some assaults well enough but didn't straighten out quickly enough.
He's still only 17.
He was outstanding in the European Youth Championships in Budapest when he was only 14 years of age and straight away was pitched into the World Championships in Rome in 2009.
So he's grown up in competition really.
Second last diver in this first series.
Hugo Parisi from Brazil, his third Olympic Games.
forward three and a half somersault made a very clean sound the sound is almost an indication as much as the the sight you'll get good marks here but with a 3.0 tariff you can't expect to collect too big a score nice entry though from Hugo top 15 one to come another big cheer it's the other British diver Peter Waterfield Tom Daly's synchro partner
He's the older of the two by far, age 31, and a local boy born in Walthamstow which is just a few miles away in East London.
He's got plenty of experience.
Waterfield, he's well known really for aquatic sport.
His opening dive is an arm stand back triple somersault, 3.3 tucked position.
Very nice.
Good start.
It's his fourth Olympic Games, so he knows what this level of competition is all about.
Kick out to start that handstand.
I must hold that handstand to show that the judges you were in control.
Big splash.
He's not a small man.
Powerfully built.
Not tall, 165 centimetres, but very compact, isn't he?
And a 66 for Peter, so room to improve and he'll need to in this hot field.
And that completes the first series of dives.
It's a long scoreboard to give you, but right at the top there, German Sanchez, Gleb Galperin, and the two Chinese divers, Lin Yue and Qu Bo, both right up there.
Bondar, Sasha Klein, some experienced divers.
Now, maybe one or two who might have been hoping for more, like Matthew Mitchum and David Budaya and Nick McCrory.
But these differences in points can be caught up fairly quickly.
Tom Daley on the line there in 18th position.
He will be believing he can only get better.
They'll feel a lot better though from having got into the competition, got that first nervous dive out of the way and start to settle into their routines.
As we've said, 32 divers means it's sort of a long evening when you're in a final with just 12 then you're in the water quickly and the whole competition gets a lot more momentum.
Though the organisation here is excellent how swiftly they get them standing at different levels of the board and ready to go and keep the entertainment going.
Yeah, just under half an hour for the first 32 dives, so we can expect half an hour per dive, per series if you like, as Galperin gets ready for his armstand reverse triple.
Age 27, born in Moscow, five foot nine.
Terrible injury problems.
He's had eight operations on his back and knee and didn't compete in 2010 and 2011.
He broke his leg as well back in 2006.
This is a dangerous sport.
Yeah and no wonder he thought about flagging it all away but his family convinced him he should keep going and he's had a very good second dive here to confirm his position near the top of the standings.
Two good dives from Gleb Galperin.
Maybe these older, more experienced divers can bring that extra measure of composure to their performance.
That's the first dive in the 90s.
Lin Yue, reverse three and a half somersault.
Oh, he's a little short on the entry there.
Beautiful through the air, as always, is the top Chinese divers.
see he just didn't kick out early enough and he's not vertical at all although somehow he manages to make such a small splash that's great control underneath the water to pull that bubble down with him
Like many of the divers here, they did take the chance to get a feel of the pool by competing in a World Cup event, which was held here at the Aquatic Centre in February, where he finished sixth.
Victor Ortega, somebody who really likes to get on with it once he gets up on that board.
Yes.
He'll help move the competition along in his own way.
Forward three and a half.
Again, really the only problem here that the divers mostly have is ripping that entry.
67.5 for Victor Anton Zakharov World Championship silver and bronze in the synchro events.
26 year old with his second dive back three and a half somersault very good control the entry beautifully some strength there and impressed his team got a bit of ground to make up really from his opening dive very tight there
chest and thighs together.
Some of them grip all the way around the back of their legs there.
One or two of them just like to hold it more to the side but you can really pull it in can't you?
That's a good shot there under the water the way they spread their arms out that helps to pull the air down with them the bubbles and create a better entry.
Timofey Hodajic with an arm stand back triple somersault tucks.
3.3 the difficulty here which is as high as his tariff of dives go.
Oh dear that was um that wasn't so special and the crowd quite mooted with their applause
These dives do give an impression without actually analyzing them into elements all the way down, which the judges are doing.
So the crowd, the good crowd here, very quickly getting a feel for what's going to go down well.
Well, the size of the splash alone was the giveaway for the crowd.
And the fours, four and a halfs, that's tough for that chick to come back from.
Four more dives though.
It can be done.
It's just you make it hard for yourself.
Put pressure on.
these divers have to qualify for this competition either through the world championships last year or being continental champion this is Ri Hyun Joo or having dived at the world cup so they've all earned the right to be here very tidy through the air second jump off the platform as the toes left and then came on again and
They've got to pull out of that rotation and the speed they generate then and that's where the core strength and those stomach muscles really come into play where they've got to basically put the brakes on in midair.
James Connor made a nervous start I think it's fair to say with an opening 66.
He was another one who was injured back in 2010 and trained for a long time with back pain.
18 months it went on and eventually he had to give himself a rest.
But he's back now.
Back three and a half somersault.
Tucked.
Very nice.
A big improvement on his first die, particularly with the entry from a 17 year old.
Looks like he might have a couple of wrist issues as well.
All these divers learn to cope with injury and compete with it if they can.
This is really going to lift his score.
The tuck is quite split, but it does allow them to go through the air a bit more quickly.
79.2.
He's picked up a few barks there.
Tell by his body language he feels a bit more encouraged there.
Martin Wolfram from Germany.
20 year old.
77.4 was his opening dive.
You're starting to get a feel for what are the kind of marks we can see helping the divers progress to the next round.
Biggish splash.
Semi-final will be progress for him.
He competed at the World Championships last year.
That was his first really big international competition, finished 20th.
So he could get into the top 18 here.
That would be a good games for him.
And then you never know.
This is the the inward three and a half we saw a lot of in the first series.
Oh, beautiful.
A good head.
He only had a 61.5 with his first dive and he kept that in so tight to the platform.
Just take your breath away.
Watch here.
But it allows him to get that more vertical position.
He's not pushing out too far away from the platform.
If you're brave enough to keep it in that close, you can get more vertical and he has taken some reward for his risk.
it's a hard-in-mouth moment though when you look at those replays and it all happens so quickly the replays really give you the chance to appreciate the sheer courage of these of these divers they know what they're doing but even so it's a 25 point improvement on with his second dive a bit olexander bonda now from ukraine pretty flying himself into uh
You do tend to get the Eastern Europeans to really attack it in that almost aggressive way.
He's jumping way out into the pool here and that just makes it a little tougher to get that vertical position.
A nice contrast really to the previous diver with what we're talking about getting into the water at the right angle.
four and a half somersaults.
He's got to generate there.
He's got to get the the height and the speed going, hasn't he?
And then put those brakes on.
Eighty-three two five though with that difficulty of three seven.
That really helps.
Jihoo Park from Korea.
In with three and a half somersault.
He's got work to do to try and
quick yeah and little under rotated at the finish to create that big splash but again a little gasp from the crowd as you see how tight he is to the board there i think that his hair might have touched the platform but fortunately not his head all fine kicks it out but over does it and that's the giveaway splash for a 67.2
Victor Mini Baef.
Also a three-meter diver as well.
Sixth in the ten-meter synchro though already.
So he's
Very good.
This is his toughest dive with a 3.7 tariff.
He's got a couple of three sixes in there as well.
Fairly savage cut after the preliminaries.
They almost cut the field in half from 32 to 18.
A camera that slides down the pole and gives you that look and some sense of the pace.
86.95, so into the top five for the moment, but plenty of dives to come in this second lot.
Next up, German Sanchez, the synchro silver medalist, likes this pool.
He was here in February and got a silver there as well.
forward two and a half somersault three twists there.
Well, there was plenty of difficulty involved with the three point eight tariff.
He opened up, of course, with an eighty nine one.
To be up near the top of the standings at the feet rolling over.
So he's not going to replicate that.
Difficulty will help.
a lot of control during that dive and he just couldn't manage to quite hold the right entry position there.
Eighty-one seven.
Still thereabouts.
In good shape to progress.
Riley McCormick from Canada down in nineteenth place.
So, he's just below the cut.
Needs to keep improving.
Back
3.6 this one so he can make up ground here.
A few Canadians in the crowd perhaps, letting the judges know they approve.
A little bit of loss of leg form at the top of that dive.
The ankles should have come together a bit quicker than that.
And just a moderate size splash.
His ankles are all over the place.
So he didn't really capitalize on the difficulty there.
79-2 though, more than respectable.
It could have been more.
Coach being put in his place.
Matthew Mitchum, the defending champion.
He feels that the injuries he's had in recent years has made him one of the underdogs here tonight and he is quite happy with that.
That should have improved his position, you think?
Well, 3.3 the tariff.
I don't think we've seen this dive yet from anyone else.
And it's almost a blind kick out, isn't it?
You've got to try and reach that vertical position with a little less to go by.
The defending Olympic champion, of course.
So much expected of him.
74 to 5.
Gizmurvic didn't muck around.
Roger is right into it.
It's very noticeable how some want to really compose themselves and while we're watching the replays and getting those results of course the officials quickly get them moving up there and ready to go and some of them really are ready to go.
Very nice entry from Gizmervik.
Trains in Sweden.
There's no 10 meter platform facility in Norway.
It's a bit of a trail brazer for Norway there in the diving.
Unlike Francesco Di Lomo, Italy have had their stars in the past.
His second dive.
Forward three and a half somersault.
Well, another impressive entry and it's just a sense that the standard is now starting to lift midway through this second series that knows not quite on the knees, but the real impression is with the entry and it was a beauty.
And so eights, eight and a half, there's a couple of nines in there as well.
They might get rejected, but they will, in fact, overall, though, pretty healthy effort.
76.5 lost the two nines of course in the scoring system as you can see them being crossed out there now Christopher Eskilsson from Sweden in with three and a half somersault 13th in round one so he'll be reasonably encouraged by his opening dive
Great entry.
A second look here.
Very tight tuck position, spots the water.
Not quite 100% vertical, but you need a second look to see that.
It's all about the entry.
He's competed at the last two world championships and never got out of the qualifying stage, so he's giving himself a bit of a chance here, perhaps.
76.8.
And he's in equal seventh position, moving up from 13th.
Now, Eric Sain did not get off to a great start.
He was right down the bottom of the pecking order in 30th, in with three and a half somersault.
And he needs to get this a lot more impressively.
Well, maybe it was better, but it needed to be better than that, if I can put it as simply as that.
Like a lot of these divers, he was taken along to the pool by mum or dad and they have a swim gym program in Canada that he turned up at one day and thought he rather liked it and his diving career took off.
As Steve said, a lot of these divers progress from gymnastics or trampolining.
One or two have had injuries and think rather mistakenly this might be a slightly, can't be a softer option can it?
A different option we'll say.
62.4 there for Eric Sane.
So move on to Brian Lomas.
Forward four and a half somersault tucks there.
3.7 the tariff.
He's named in part after one of your great footballers, Brian Robson.
So his dad must be a huge football fan back in Malaysia.
Brian Robson wouldn't have held back, I can tell you that.
He'd have been diving, he really would have given it the full face of the bat.
The trouble for this Brian was that he didn't quite straighten out the legs below the hips here and he's come in at a bit of an angle.
Malaysia never won an Olympic gold medal before these games so it would be a great incentive but might still be in the dreams perhaps.
The second half just letting him down a little as we move swiftly on.
Ivan Garcia now up in ninth place right on the edge of that board back three and a half somersault that in itself a real test of nerve for most people
Oh, very good.
And they do have to take their time in that position and make sure they've got the composure right on the edge of the board there.
No spring to be had out of concrete, so they really need the power out of the legs.
And he has controlled that entry beautifully, Garcia, and he's getting a sprinkling of nines for this dive, which will really move him up the standings.
Third.
It's a great camera angle that top shot looking right down really gives you an idea of the view from the top there which is formidable.
Nick McCrory from the United States.
Arm stand back double somersault one and a half twist.
He's 13th equal.
This in itself a test getting right to the edge of that board.
basically three stories up in the air.
agonizing weight at the top there.
He was wasn't I just thought is he in control here is he got all his thoughts together but the execution was fine he did kick out a little horizontally and I was wondering if he was going to get through all that he had to but he reached a beautiful position for the entry and it was well in control.
The nerve at the top of that board to just hold on hold on until you know, you're absolutely right We know how much they practice but even so in this atmosphere with this pressure and expectation You really have got to admire their skill in their sheer nerve putting the towel down quite a few of them there just to get that a little bit of extra grip and feel
Jose Guerra of Cuba, back three and a half somersault.
Had a poor first dive, needs this to be good.
Oh it's not, oh dear.
Wow.
Your heart goes out doesn't it?
Yeah and his head drops, he knows all too well that this went seriously wrong.
kicked out too early and he's almost hit horizontally.
Well he did complete the dive.
If you do complete the dive you will get a score like if you just sort of opt out half through then it will be deemed to be incomplete and that is a zero but to be fair the crowd were really supportive there I thought and sympathetic.
the crowd realize that what these men are doing they could never do so there's that respect in with three and a half somersault piked made a good start with a 78 four may not get full value here with some problems on the entry i like his form through the air wonderful position there spots the water then twists and
Must be square on as well as vertical.
He wasn't quite either.
71.75 though.
Next up the synchro bronze medallist from last week David Boudia who does confess that he's been to see sports psychologists because he doesn't have a great deal of confidence with heights which is a bit unfortunate when you're standing on the edge of a 10 meter board but he's got an in with three and a half somersault now.
I think he's got the problem sorted, but I'd need the same, I think.
He attacked that though, didn't he?
Number of divers to score in the 80s with his first.
Not quite so prodigious with his second.
Hands are flat as they enter the water, they're not pointed and that helps create a hole for the body to follow into the water with.
73.6 for Badiah.
Next up, the favourite Chu Bo.
Got 25 perfect 10s when he got a historic 609.20 at the Diving World Series in Beijing last year.
oh my goodness what an entry how does he do it he does it with a bow and there was no splash it could have been a pea entering the water and the judges love it there's a 10 in there look at that entry position
Well, a couple of those, well, the two 10s, unfortunately for him, get cast aside, but it is a very high score for Trubot.
What an impression to leave.
99.75.
They really are poker-faced throughout their program, the Chinese divers.
They really don't like to let their emotions come through so controlled all the way through the evening.
And it's a long evening for them.
Sascha Klein now from Germany.
Forward four and a half somersault.
Well he got away with a good entry there having not really established a vertical position.
He might feel he's in that group outside the big guns, challenging perhaps for medal honours.
That's the next 24 hours passes.
Plenty of somersaults to get through.
Good entry, just hips slightly bent there, but 88.8, we're not going to argue with that kind of mark.
A climb into fourth position at the moment, early in the prelims.
Vadim Kaptur now from Belarus with work to do in the three and a half somersault with which to make some progress.
3.2, the tariff.
And again, one of these inward dives that has the crowd a little concerned about how close he was to the platform.
Us two, judge it for yourself here.
Makes a beautiful entry though.
Well, while we wait for those very solid marks indeed, the crowd are already getting excited because it's Great Britain's Tom Daley on the board next.
And he and Jessica Ennis were the two pre-games faces that you saw absolutely everywhere in the country.
Jessica's got her gold, which doubles the pressure on Tom.
In with three and a half somersault tucked.
Not really settled yet.
That's better.
Only a 73.8 for his first dive.
Can't let the field get away from him here.
Almost a third of the way through the competition.
Needs something in the high 70s if he can muster it.
And he's been a star ever since he was 14 years of age in Beijing.
The youngest competitor in the team outside of swimming, Britain's second youngest ever Olympian.
World champion of course in Rome in 2009 at 15 and it's been one long marathon of expectation but he's getting there.
and the high 70s is what he has achieved so that improvement will help.
Andrea Chiarabini from Italy, arm stand back triple somersault for the 17 year old from Rome.
Didn't want to hold it too long, he was ready
Well, that's an entry that Troubault would be pleased with.
It's barely a ripple.
Pulled it in nicely.
The judge is not too impressed.
I just wonder whether he wasn't in a controlled handstand position for long enough for the judges to be happy.
Bit too anxious to get on with it, basically.
must give the impression of control and time.
They have to have control.
It's just not going to happen otherwise.
Hugo Parisi from Brazil.
Gives you a sense of how far up it is doesn't it?
That low angle.
In with three and a half somersault.
Never got beyond the preliminary round in two Olympic Games before.
A little bit heavy perhaps.
Only one diver left in this second series.
And there's an Englishman.
Big splash there.
Doesn't help Figo Parisi's cause.
Spots the water.
Just not quite there.
Again, the crowd are willing on the final diver of 32, Peter Waterfield from Great Britain, who's had his injury problems with the virus before the last World Championships.
He's had shoulder injuries and neck injury more recently.
But the 31-year-old is still here and competing and ready to do an inward three and a half somersault.
Well, the crowd reaction told you most things about the entry.
Well, he only had a 66 with his first dive and he needed improvement.
Not a problem.
And the problem is what he's had here as the legs go way over.
He's just got through it too quickly.
It's over rotated.
Got a silver in Athens in 2004 with Leon Taylor in the 10 meter synchronized.
Well, he's nearly at the bottom of the field with that second dive, unfortunately, for Waterfield at 31st.
So that is a big mountain to climb.
Chubo ascending to his customary position there at the league, Gleb Galper in German Sanchez, Sascha Klein, Ivan Navarro, the Mexicans continuing to do well.
David Budaya has pulled up a little bit as well.
Tom Daley up to 15th.
He might have to come out of the pack as it were to try to get into a good position rather like running a 10k out there on the track not too far away where you get through those qualifying rounds in shape and look to build.
That's certainly what the crowd in this fantastic 17,000-seater Aquatic Centre will be hoping
Down there on that caption, these are the ones who really are just wanting to be back here in the morning and to make their Olympic Games more than a six dive wonder.
Peter Waterfield there, the other home favourite with a huge amount of work to do.
Matthew Mitchum also on the bubble sitting in the sixteenth position so he can't afford to have things go wrong but Cleb Galperin has made a very good start two excellent dives that would probably be the worst of his three Galperin was first after the first rotation second after the second forward three and a half somersault there for the Olympic Games bronze medalist in Beijing
Didn't make the synchro team.
And just a 66 for his third drive.
That's a disappointing one for Galperin.
Interestingly enough, neither of China's gold medal winning 10 meter synchro team actually made the individual competition, which is just astonishing.
Lin Yue.
Oh goodness me.
Back three and a half somersault there and he's starting to show his pedigree I think.
And now we're seeing why they come to this event as favorites.
What a position he adopts.
What an entry he achieves and what splash.
Slicing into the water there.
Look how tight he is there.
Really hugging those legs.
That's enormous flexibility.
They're not just slim.
Look at the power and the muscle definition on his thighs and the push-up and the stomach muscle strength to pull out of those dives.
There's a 100-point dive.
Victor Ortega from Colombia.
previously competed at the Olympics in the synchro event.
Arm stand back triple somersault, tucked.
No respectable.
He's in 25th after the second dive so he's fighting to be back tomorrow morning.
Just didn't really control the entry.
He's got three more dives to try and consolidate his position.
Anton Zakharov just missed out in a synchro medal back in 2004 at the Olympic Games.
Well, those high speed forward, four and a half somersaults tucked with a 3.7 tariff, if you nail it.
Well, it always looked like he did have it in control, not too horizontal with his takeoff from the platform.
The ankle's just slightly apart, made a good job of the entry.
Some from column A, some from column B, as we say.
And he's got his little support crew here.
certainly tell the Ukrainians in that very distinctive kit they wear.
Spot them a mile off.
Anything in the 80s you'll take and he's had 72 and 88 and an 83.
Timofey Odechik he was right down in 30th position forward three and a half some assaults was the intention there.
He's come up short hasn't he?
Never got through it.
He's just struggling to reach his best in this competition and
See his head well away from the knees compared to our two Chinese stars.
Just a different position.
He can still make that work but he didn't on that occasion.
There on that 10 meter board from the Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
Just 16 years of age.
Arm stand back, triple somersault.
Now, how quickly will he be into the dive from his hold position?
Up very quickly.
Oh, he's not got it there.
he can do it again but there is a there's a time on this and more than anything else this is a major test good luck well he had to hurry that to get into the position again and and a reminder of just how big that part of the dive is a test and not just to be taken for granted what they're doing before they even set off
So he had to rush it in the end and under some pressure he's flopped over, over rotated, big splash and it will be a difficult dive to come back from.
The feeling of panic when you lose that then when it is all about composure at the top of that board must be absolutely unimaginable.
So he's really been punished there.
The score of eighteen.
That is that's crippling.
That is that's awful.
Jimmy Connor, seventeen-year-old Australian.
In with three and a half somersaults.
Back in twenty-fourth.
Needs to put on a bit of a show here if he's going to be back in the morning or else he could be having a late night
Well, I was concerned for him because he seemed to be there an age convincing himself when to go and yet he's done a good job here.
Must be almost like getting the yips, you know, golfers and even they call it dartitis in darts when you can't let go.
He's got it right in the end.
Well played.
Give some concession to his youth here, one of the younger divers at 17.
76.8.
So one in the mid 60s and two in the high 70s.
He's hanging around there.
Martin Vulfrom from Germany.
He was here in February in the World Cup, finished ninth at this height.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Oh, good job.
And he was 19th after the second dive.
So he too is right on that cut.
This needed to be as good as it turned out to be.
This is a wonderful entry.
Martin Wolfram has really surged up the standings with this one.
Not sure how much of that lack of a square position the judges will see.
They haven't punished him for it really with an 87-4-5, some nines in there.
That's a great effort.
from Cuba.
Back three and a half somersault.
He's down twenty-second position.
So, it's within range.
The difficulty here is three point six for the back three and a half somersault.
Well, didn't quite get there and this was his highest tariff dive or he's got another one coming for his last that's also 3.6 but these are the ones you really need to make most use of.
He'd gone to the semi-final in last year's World Championship so he would have probably come to London expecting at least to come back for a second round of dives but this is the world's best.
It's going to be difficult.
and a big splash on entry.
Therefore, and a sixty-four point eight.
That won't help him.
Ukrainian Alexander Bondar, eighteen-year-old from Lugansk with a arm stand back double somersault two and a half twist.
I mean, he's up in sixth place.
Needs to just get that
Still there.
No.
Has to take something out of the shoulders being in that position that long.
seemed to be almost too keen to get into the twist before he'd really got himself away from the board.
Yeah and he was bent at the hips, bad position entering the water, the ankles came apart also so there was some leg form issues throughout the dive.
They only came together at the end but the entry was not too special so a 57.6 and Bondar is going to plummet down the rankings.
went all said and done after the third.
Consistency, that's the big test across six dives.
Ki-hoo Park from Korea, 20 year old.
Back three and a half somersault.
Oh and he's overdone that one as well.
He's struggling really, Park.
Not his night.
It must be so hard to put the previous dive behind you and start from scratch every time.
It's a bit like a golfer stepping up on the tee again after a double bogey and needing to clear all the negatives out and starting again with each dive.
He just never got into a really tight tuck position.
Even the split tuck would have helped him get through those rotations more quickly.
So some technique issues there for Park.
Victor Mini Vive.
Synchro partner of Ilya Zakharov.
Reverse three and a half somersault another long wait at the top there.
Very nice.
Eleventh after two dives.
I don't think he's going to give up any ground with that one.
Half an arm movement at the top there.
It looked as though he wasn't quite sure and then he was all very positive.
Judges are fairly happy with it.
The feet just rolled over at the very end but very positive entry.
and Nivaev after a rough start a 67 with his first dive 86.95 is second and then 82.5 for his third so starting to produce it
Next up, it's twenty-year-old German Sanchez from Guadalajara in Mexico who's having an excellent games.
The silver medal from the Syncro already in his kit.
And it's third after two dives.
And now with an arm stand back, triple somersault.
How long will it take him to get into that key position?
Legs wide and closing.
Well, he looked more confident at the top than he did at the bottom, where the entry was less than ideal.
He's got a little bit of room to play with, having come into this series well positioned.
former junior world silver medalist at 10 meters.
That was only in 2010, so they are so young, these competitors, many of them.
Father's a professional footballer, so he should know a little bit about diving.
There's one or two footballers one could say that they've dived a little bit.
That's unkind, right?
That's well worked in, though.
Nice segue.
Seventy, seventy five point nine for his third as we move on to Riley McCormick from Canada.
14th in with three and a half somersault.
Lovely that McCormick will be proud of that one I think especially the entry.
This is a zero splash dive if you like.
He just pulls that water down with him, the air that he's created, the arms separate.
There's a bit of a technique to this, to ripping the entry, and he's giving him 9 out of 10 for the entry, not that they separate them, but, you know, sitting up here we can.
And an 80.
From Arizona State University, combining his diving with his studies in the United States.
He wants our job, a career in broadcasting.
Matthew Mitchum.
I think he needs to make a statement now, Mitchum.
He's just had a pedestrian couple of first two dives.
Him with three and a half somersault for the defending champion.
That's better.
Well, the evidence shows that he knows how to pull out the big one on the big occasion, but he has left himself a little bit more work than he would have expected.
very good entry and he's going to pull some eights and a very split tuck position but then pulls it back together again for the entry competed in the three meter springboard at the last Olympics didn't qualify for the final but now concentrating and he's got a mark in the 80s to perhaps move him up the rankings we'll see when everyone's finished three
Back three and a half somersault.
He's 12th.
competed at one metre in the World Championships, one metre of course not an Olympic event.
His problem there was that even in the tuck position his feet weren't aligned and the judges side on would have been able to see that as perhaps you did too.
That's an unusual error really.
And the 64-3 fire for Gizmovic.
Looks to be good camaraderie around the pool.
We love seeing that at the Olympics, even at the very top level, that the athletes are friends.
We've seen plenty of that in all the sports across the games, which has been great.
Francesco De Luomo, because it's a lonely place at the top of that board, in with three and a half somersault.
Very good.
Francesco will come up smiling.
You sometimes get a sense of how the diver feels about it, how quickly they come to the surface.
Well, I hear some of this applause.
I thought that went all right.
What's the crowd think?
Well, they liked it.
He was a European silver medalist back in 2004.
So he's had a good length career to know how to deal with these occasions.
An eighty one six.
Christopher Eskilsson from Sweden who's been doing too badly at 12 equal after three dives and now an arm stand back triple somersault.
Well he executed the dive okay but he didn't look convincing in the handstand he once he reached a position where he felt confident he did move but he hadn't held it for long
Judges aren't too unhappy with him.
He was pretty vertical for the entry, even if it wasn't a low splash affair.
And a seventy-two point six.
These the boys that are sort of on the bubble, it brings its own pressure when you get about halfway through the competition, you realize that you can't muck up a dive.
Eric Sainz said it was a dream come true just to be at the Olympics and admitted that he'd set his stall out to get to the final was his ambition, but he's got some work to do.
Armstand back double somersault, two and a half twist.
He's back in twenty-ninth.
Oh dear, that was short.
He almost fell off the platform.
He's had a couple of poor dives, only three competitors below him.
And I just wonder what's going on here for Eric.
He's a better diver than this.
Well, he'll look at that, as I'm sure he will, and realize that he can do better.
Canadian champion at the individual and the synchro events.
Picked up medals, Pan American Games, Commonwealth Games, but this is a big step up, the Olympic Games.
And a fifty-five point eight for Eric.
He's going to be disheartened by that.
Brian Lomas from Malaysia.
Trains in China where facilities you won't be surprised to discover are top quality.
Back three and a half somersault.
Oh well that's seriously overcooking a fairly straightforward dive.
That's a shame for him.
The crowd reaction told you everything there, let alone what the judges will make of it.
Just tumbling into it like a chimney being demolished.
Yeah, that's a 29.7.
Such a low score that it could be hard to recover from with three dives to come.
And he too is better than that, if you look at his past record.
Now the Mexicans are on a bit of a charge in this diving competition.
Ivan Garcia, fifth.
The Synchro Silver Medalist.
Pan-American double champion.
Seventh at the Worlds last year.
This is a competition that he's familiar with.
A standard he can match.
still only 18 so he is obviously progressing in his career the inward four and a half somersault tucked 4.1 the tariff here a big one
Well, OK.
But when you've got that big tariff, you really are looking to play your joker, as they say, and get the almost the double points.
Just look for the problems he had by the time he reached the water here that the legs weren't where he wanted them to be.
They were they weren't straight from the hips and they weren't together at the ankles.
And the judges will get in for that.
Just a slight twist.
77.9 though and the difficulty certainly helps boost the score.
On to Nick McCrory from Durham North Carolina studying maths at Duke University so he'll be able to work out his own scores quicker than the judges perhaps.
Well we do have a little bit of computer aid.
Big quick forward four and a half somersault worth 3.7
Different ways to take the photo these days.
He had the tablet out.
Just watch the entry here.
He made a good job with the zero, almost zero splash, but close to a vertical position.
That certainly helped.
But I think the judges could see that he hadn't achieved a vertical position.
Jose Guerra from Cuba.
Bringing up the rear at the moment.
It's worth pausing.
Look at that great score that Lin here.
He's now 15 points clear of the field.
We haven't finished this third series, but 100 points will help you every time.
Oh, very nice for Jose Guerra.
That'll please the Cubans.
We've got a silver at the World Championships at 10 metres back in 2005, so suddenly finding that sort of form.
Well, he was nowhere after the second series.
He had a disastrous second dive.
He's put that well out of his mind to produce a stellar effort.
Maybe a bit of encouragement there, not just for Jose, but also for every other diver who's starting to think that he might have missed the boat.
That was brilliant.
As I said, it's his fourth Olympic Games.
He has got diving pedigree.
That's livened the crowd up as well.
Sebastian Villa now.
He's 17th.
Cannot afford to drop his standards with an arm stand back triple somersault.
Oh, but he has.
And that's well short of the vertical.
He's scanning back through Guerra's dive.
So 58, 21, 92.
So a model of inconsistency.
Proves he's a fighter.
Yeah.
Well, that's a shame for Villa, Castaneda, Sebastian Villa.
Agony for the coaches and the family and everybody else here supporting.
Fair old trek from Colombia.
David Budaya, 10th so far.
It's not as far as it is from Australia Roger, I'll tell you.
Very true, very true.
Very nice.
It was like a second splash if you will.
He didn't quite control the air under the water there.
It was a funny one.
Those four and a half somersaults.
Tunked.
There was a lot of tumbling momentum to try and bring under control at the end for the entry.
They're putting him forward as the best American platform diver among the men since the great Greg Louganis.
One of the iconic names from diving in the past when America absolutely dominated at this event before China decided to enter and spoiled their party a little bit.
Well, he inspired many to take up the sport, didn't he?
Such a master of it.
Springboard and platform.
and that famous crack on the board which we do not want to see repeated.
Chubo now the star.
Oh and again he sets a very high standard nice and tight into the platform.
The crowd is being treated here with some world-class diving particularly from the two Chinese.
Just 19 years of age.
He's the son of a factory worker from Sichuan.
Uncle was a gymnast, and the big marks are coming out for the big dives now.
Throw out the two nines and the ten, and you're just left with nine and a halfs for Troubo.
And a 94.05.
And now he leads Lin Ye.
China won too.
No shock there.
Sasha Klein though, wanting to make the statement in this preliminary round that he is a genuine medal contender.
We'll worry about the colour of that medal afterwards.
An armstand back triple somersault were 3.5 for the German diver.
Excellent job.
Good effort with that one, Sasha Klein.
He's not going to give up too much ground with that, I wouldn't think, having come into this third dive in fourth position.
He's a soldier, serves in the army, who obviously are very accommodating and give him plenty of training time, I would imagine.
Looks happy with it, and a 92.75.
Why wouldn't you be?
That's his best dive so far.
Eighty-one, eighty-eight, and ninety-two.
I think he might be on the bookies blackboard that one.
I think that Sasha Klein could be somebody who is in contention.
Although the way the Chinese are starting to emerge don't want them just to be all competing for third place.
Vadim Kaptur now.
He did look to be struggling in his departure from the
Got through it, forward double somersault with a twist after that armstand.
Not even allowed to enjoy his dive again and wait for the scores because you know who is on next.
He's got some eights in there though, Vadim Kaptur, for a score of 74-4.
And 16th just needs to keep him pressing.
Tom Daley, who was given the honour of making the first dive in this pool when it was officially opened.
July last year with exactly one day, one year to go to the day to the opening of the games.
Arm stand back, triple somersault.
He's back in 15th.
It's reminding you 18 to move on to the semi, so it's got to keep some good dives coming.
Well, he's recovered that well.
He had a moment of unsteadiness in the handstand, collected himself and executed well.
Crowds absolutely love him.
He's had problems as a youngster.
Obviously the terribly sad story of his father dying, who was such an influence obviously and a massive active supporter.
He was bullied at school for a while and such a nice chap as well.
He's put such a nice dive in there and I think an 89.25 and Tom Daley starting to find the confidence needed to just move on to the next part of the competition.
Doing a bit of a Jess Annis there just withdrawing into himself and keeping that composure in between dives and they've got a long wait.
Andrea Chiarabini back three and a half somersault.
He's way down in 28th.
He still might be down there too after over rotating there and making a bit of a mess of the entry.
At 17, these teenage divers have a lot of chance to come again and continue to progress.
I think you have to taste this level of competition and the pressure that comes with it to deal with it and then make the most of it next time.
It's a rare Olympian who steps up first time and nails it.
Especially at that age.
You're used to seeing that with the gymnastics where also they start frighteningly young.
Oh they do but not as young as they used to.
They've made a few restrictions to age and the women have to be turning 16 the year of the Olympic competition.
Hugo Parisi from Brazil.
He's not having the best of days either.
That back three and a half somersault.
And he, by contrast, Hugo is 28.
He just never quite got there, went in at quite an angle and made quite a splash, but not in a good way.
They've done that dive so many times, but it's all about delivering it on the day.
Peter Waterfield from Great Britain, who is having a very disappointing evening so far, but the terrific crowd here, predictably right behind him.
forward four and a half somersault well this is his big dive it's the 3.7 difficulty and he's about to make up a serious amount of ground here the crowd doing their best to influence the judges he was competing back in 1997 at world championship level
So he does know how to put these things behind him.
Well, that was a wonderful dive.
That's a view as he goes past the judges.
He's got to get those feet together.
They can't afford to blink the judges, can you?
No, it's there's actually two panels work through this long session to make sure that the job's done with fresh eyes.
Ninety four, three, five.
Well, that's well done him.
That'll help.
He looks as though he's pleased with that, quite rightly so, showing his fighting qualities.
Let's check on that leaderboard then.
Halfway through the competition, Ju Bo leading from the front, but Sascha Klein from Germany.
up there in second place.
Linue, German Sanchez, Galper in second Mexican, even Garcia, Tom Daly progressing up to ninth.
And just after here, the next caption will give you where the cut is.
These are the people who are really under the pressure at the moment.
It's not those at the top.
It's Kaptur, Bondar, Jimmy Connor, Victor Ortega.
They're all around that cut at eighteen.
That is their objective and it is tight around there.
Half a dozen points will make all the difference.
Peter Waterfield made up some ground with that third dive but still 17 away from that little group on the bubble so he's got to have a couple more good dives.
But it can be done.
You only need three or four ahead of you to stumble.
And again, they're keeping very tightly to schedule here.
One of the features when you go from event to event, not just in the diving pool, is the competition organization, how quickly they get every sport ready.
And the whole thing is like clockwork, really, to a very strict time schedule.
So back to the top of the order we go.
Gleb Galperin from Russia, double world champion and Olympic bronze medalist.
Oh, lovely dive to start the fourth.
And he's never been out of the top five in the competition this evening.
And I think he might just stay there.
That was well executed, confidently done.
This man, as we've discussed, has come back from a series of terrible injuries and a host of operations and still performing at the top.
comes from a sporting family.
His father works in diving for the Russian Ministry of Sport, and his mother is a master of sports in gymnastics, so he's got it from both sides there.
Plenty of guidance.
Couple in the 80s and 91, and they're just that bad dive of 66 for his third, but let's enjoy linear.
Four and a half, somersault.
Speed of that.
Well, he can certainly somersault, but he didn't quite pull it up in quite the right way as he flipped over the feet here.
That split tuck position to get through the splash means that he won't be getting nines.
actually broke the 600 barrier for points in the 2010 National Championships in China.
603.45, an astonishing total.
And he's rattling up.
They are at 92 there.
They're just so consistent.
He's to average 100 per dive.
Staggering.
Outrageous, yeah.
Victor Ortega from Colombia.
20th he was in with a shout in with three and a half somersault that needs to make progress.
He's planning to be a lawyer when he finishes competing and give something back to the sport which is lovely to hear.
Hope he's not done yet.
Interesting the height there off the board he got trying to get through those somersaults almost before they go back down.
What a lovely position.
Just a slightly larger splash and a seventy-three-six for Ortega.
Anton Zakharov has had more success at synchro competition than when in the individual dives.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
It's just a little arched on entry there, Roger.
He won't get the full value for it.
He's looking very solid to be back again tomorrow morning, though, unless he has a disaster later on.
Fairly tight into the platform.
He's really reaching to try and pull that entry.
He's been competing at world championship level since 2001.
He's only 26 which gives you an idea for the 16 and 17 year olds that we're seeing just how their career can develop over the long term and they could be back for two, three Olympics.
Timofey Hordyachik of Belarus.
in with three and a half somersault 31st personal pride perhaps his main motivation here ah that's a better one he's had a couple of indifferent dives for the etchick
pride might indeed have motivated him here he's uh just managed to put the poor dives to one side come up with a better one if not quite the splash he would have liked the divers don't see the splash but i'm sure they get a sense of it and a 68.8 for him
Now, the Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
He's a 16 year old.
The back three and a half somersault.
This is a competition for
from Pyongyang.
He's just finding that he can't bring his best dives to this.
I wonder if we will perhaps see better from him when another Olympic cycle rolls past.
But that's a very poor entry at this level.
Only five foot one.
He must be one of the smallest divers in the competition, but rather deflating marks there.
Now, Jimmy Connor, the 17-year-old is just at 19th.
Arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twists from Melbourne but he lives in Brisbane, trains there, splits the family up.
Her dad lives in Melbourne,
Enormous sacrifices that the families make.
All sorts of ways to get to the handstand and this is Jim's.
He's there.
It's an important thing.
And he just over rotated on the entry there.
It's a big strain on a young lad, not just competing here, but as we mentioned there, when the family has to split up to back him and the whole family invests in that sporting future is a terrific pressure on a young lad.
Yes, Brisbane, some 1600 kilometres from Melbourne.
It's no overnight trip, I can tell you, to get the family back together.
A 64 there for James.
Martin Wolfram from Dresden in Germany.
Tenth, back three and a half somersault.
Having a pretty good evening so far.
Nearly.
See what went wrong here was mainly again the most obvious error is in quite a nice position here.
Nose to the knees, but didn't straighten it out in time for an impressive entry.
He'd be fairly pleased so far though.
He's sitting comfortably in the frame and just has to keep it steady and get on with his work really.
Yeah, 3.6 difficulty helped him out there to achieve an 84.6.
He should be alright.
Yancla Aguilar from Cuba.
Started diving when he was just six years of age.
Arm stand back double somersault, one and a half twist.
back down in twenty seconds.
So, he needs to pull out a solid score here to keep in touch.
Certainly got through the twist nice and early but a little bit of an angle on the entry.
Just a touch short
See how the hands have got to move.
They tend to put one behind the back of the head and one down the side and they're straight away then changing hand position as they as the dive unravels there.
Seventy point four for Agri there.
Awful lot to think about in what amounts to about 1.8 seconds the dive takes.
A lot of moving parts to get aligned at the last moment for the entry.
Bondor.
Back three and a half somersault there and he's 18th.
He has just nailed one there.
Alexander Bondor.
He's going to be happy with the score here surely because he has ripped a wonderful entry and the nines are coming for Bondor.
That should really have taken him away from that position right on the edge of the cut at 18th.
That's just a bit too uncomfortable going into the closing rounds.
Don't think of Ukraine as a place where they play billiards, but he does.
Good hobby away from diving.
Everyone needs a distraction from their main focus.
Got to find other things to do.
You get crazy with only one focus.
Jiho Park from Korea.
24th, reverse two and a half somersault.
Just 2.9 the tariff here.
It's not going to get him a huge amount of marks when you've got a low tariff dive.
You've got to get as much technical standard as possible to get the decent score.
And the competitors from North and South of the border in Korea, just finding this level of competition beyond them, it would seem, in these preliminaries.
So Park, a 37-7, so I don't think we will see him in action in the morning.
Victor Mini.
Arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half twists.
In eleventh position.
Three point six, the degree of difficulty here.
European silver medalist in his first Olympic games.
Getting that long hold at the top.
It was an impressive rise to handstand initially.
Held it for quite a long time and didn't execute the back end of the dive.
Through the twist, spots the water and I think that really the entry is the only thing he's going to get penalized for because the rest of the dive looked very tidy, nice leg form, good position and just can't keep the splash down.
Seventy-seven four.
Well, the Mexicans again who have a strong diving tradition having a more than respectable games.
Two silver and a bronze so far in these games.
And German Sanchez is fourth so far in this preliminary competition.
Tough dive this one, Roger.
Inward four and a half somersault.
Got to push out and then dive, haven't you?
And get through those somersaults so quickly, you've just got to rip them around to have any chance to get...
There's no running jump at these four and a half somersaults.
So that's why it attracts the 4.1.
He's through at least two before he comes back down level with that 10 metre board.
and a ninety-eight point four with a big difficulty working off those scores of eight.
He's comfortably back tomorrow and with thoughts overnight perhaps of just how much potential he can bring to bear come the end of the day.
Riley McCormick getting up into an arm stand back triple somersault for three point three.
Well, he's just over-rotated a little on the entry.
He was up to the handstand, the armstand, very confidently.
He competed in Beijing when he was just 16, finished 16th.
That's 10 metres.
And he will be looking to build on that back four years later.
It's sixty nine three for McCormick is the lowest of his four dives so far.
So ranging from that up to eighty.
Now, what are we going to get from Matthew Mitchum, the defending champion, Eminem?
Are they calling?
Well, he's a bit like a box of chocolate.
You're not sure what you're going to get.
He's been a little bit inconsistent, at least in this competition.
Reverse three and a half somersault with a three point three
splash will tell you a bit and he doesn't want to pop his head up too early he's he won't be too thrilled with the execution here he started as a trampolinist as well competing at world junior championship level nearly got to an olympics in trampolining which has become quite a popular sport in australia
He's certainly putting some pressure on himself to make tomorrow morning.
It's got to be more there.
There's obviously a lot more there.
Can he dig it out, though?
You know, returning Olympic champions has fought it so hard to replicate all the distractions that happen in the intervening years.
Amund Kismarvik from Norway, 21 year old.
That reverse two and a half somersault only had a two point seven tariff so it demands a high level of execution.
And he didn't have it Roger.
There's a major splash at the end of this.
Kicked it out quite elegantly but then the toes weren't pointed.
The angle wasn't right.
And he's being marked down.
It was very good until it wasn't.
Very few Norwegians making it to this level of competition.
Francesco Delomo from Italy.
Fifteenth back three and a half somersault.
Can't afford to get anything radically wrong.
Just needs to keep it solid to make sure he's back tomorrow.
Oh dear.
Quite a bit of water there.
And he was up so quickly.
He didn't really manage to pull the dive down into the water and minimise the splash.
He's got two dives of this difficulty, 3.3.
And he's come in at such an angle he's popped up straight away and he's not made the most of this.
Just couldn't pull the air in after him.
And a forty-one two five for Francesco.
That will not help because he's in that area between sort of fifteen and twenty.
Top eighteen to progress remember.
Christopher Eskilsson from Sweden.
Twenty-three year old.
Back three and a half somersault.
He's sixteenth just making the cut at the moment.
Oh dear and the crowd gasps and we'll just leave that one to the judges because you saw as well as we did.
He would have seen the diver before him, Duomo, in a similar position in terms of rankings make a mistake and he had a chance to capitalize just maybe move up that one more spot but if anything he's put in a worse dive 39.6 Eskilsson.
so tough the pressure but you that's what the sport is you just have to deliver it on the day can't go a goal down and pull it back in the second half it's just not that sort of an event eric sane from canada that's better he's had a fairly wretched night until now forward three and a half somersault there with a 3.0 degree of difficulty
Well, this was a dive he could manage his control and really a little bit bent in that pike position, it has to be acknowledged.
Entry a lot better.
Some very successful synchro divers do find it a different proposition when they get up there on their own and it's all about the execution.
There's no backup scores for the synchronization, which counts very heavily in the team event, as they call it.
now our friend Brian Lomas from Malaysia reverse three and a half somersault
That's better.
He's had a slightly erratic evening himself.
Some of the Malaysian support for him.
I'm sure he's a bit of a legend back home.
The nation doesn't turn out an enormous number of athletes on the world stage.
In his third Olympic Games, he carried the flag for Malaysia in the opening ceremony back in 2004.
Well, I believe he was the youngest, smallest and lightest participant.
I'm sure he managed the flag OK.
And a 74 to 5.
Back up now towards the top of the rankings with the Mexican Ivan Garcia.
Arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half twists.
Three point six, the multiplier here and he's in a decent position.
Sixth after round three and you sense real confidence in the Mexican camp.
Legs spread wide before close
Yeah, well, reasonably tidy.
3.6 the degree of difficulty, so it will be boosted by that, but there were just a question mark about whether he got through all the twists in time to straighten up and achieve that vertical position, and he was a little hinged at the hips.
Is he giving the camera away with that toe?
That is an angle, isn't it?
We've got them all covered here.
81.
For Ivan.
Ninety-one different recognized platform dives you can pick from.
Everyone a a challenge.
Some greater than others to say the least.
Nick McCraw is up next from the United States.
The Syncro Bronze
Well, rank 12th coming into this dive, number four, and I don't think he'll be giving up ground there.
That was a very decent effort.
A little bit of a splash on entry, but reaching for the sky, tucking in tight, getting through them as well, reaching for the water.
Pretty good position.
Not the smallest splash you'll see, but a very solid job done with this dive.
I'm sure he will have set himself the target of reaching the final tomorrow evening.
He's finished sixth in the World Championships last year.
79.2, his chance is not damaged by that.
Anything around the 80 keeps you just bubbling along and heading for more competition.
José Guerra.
His fourth dive is an armstand reverse triple somersault.
He's back down in 30th position
greatest ever diver and he's the oldest diver in the competition.
Oh, wow.
That's his three point four tariff.
He could just be about to make a bit of a statement here.
At thirty-three years of age.
It's his fourth Olympics.
He competed in five world championships.
So, you know, he
pulling out that level I wonder is that enough?
Well he's got a little bit of competition to come and if he can replicate that why not 95.2 and he races up to 17th but with a few drivers to come.
Well when you produce a dive of that standard you're going to be absolutely devastated if you don't make the cut.
Sebastian Villa from Colombia
Well he's going to struggle to make the cut 25th coming in to this fourth dive and the feet just roll over not not badly so marks of seven coming to us via the PA and perhaps you can hear them too and the the calculation is done and he's got a 77.7
Next up, David Budaya from the United States.
Sixteen national titles in a distinguished career.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Well, now he was eighth coming into this dive.
Some consternation there as the vertical position was certainly was not achieved.
Through the tucks early and he's looking for the water now and
The feet just rolled over.
Big splash.
The head drops.
Forty-four, five, five.
That'll send him into the trouble area.
I think he'll be alright.
Now comes the man setting all the standards.
Chubo, the nineteen-year-old, with a back three-and-a-half somersault,
Oh, and enjoy it we do.
He's averaging 90 for his first three dives.
Really gets some power off the platform straight into such a tight position.
Pulls it around, saves it a little.
He seemed to be a bit short coming to the water, but then he's got this ability to minimize the splash and rip an entry even without perfect position.
Fina's world diver of the year last year.
That's solid again.
Even when they don't reach the absolute heights, they never let their standards drop.
86.4.
He's had two of those and two dives in the nineties.
They just churn them out, don't they?
Now, Sasha Klein from Germany has had a good evening so far.
This is a back three and a half somersault.
Very nice.
in the pike position.
So it just presents a different look for the judges to consider here.
The piked obviously when they grab it behind the knees, legs straight out as opposed to the tucked when they're up there in the ball.
five foot eight.
He's a bit more powerful type of guy.
Very strongly through his dive there.
Ninety-one eight.
So he's had two scores in the nineties with dives three and four.
Vadim Kaptur.
Seventeenth.
Back two and a half
3.2, the tariff there.
Can't afford to drop too far back.
It's a steady effort.
Such a distraction for him preceding a British diver.
The crowd, not disrespectful, just excited.
And sevens here for Kaptur.
Could have been a bit tighter in there.
Thighs to chest.
And they'll still be loitering around the bubble, we think.
Right in capture.
Well, the 10 meters platform was one of the hot tickets pre-Olympic Games.
And they were all pretty hot.
And they've all turned out to see Tom Daley, who won the national under 18 title when he was only 10.
Forward four and a half somersault tucked 3.7.
Well, the crowd liked it a little more than the judges will, I think.
He was a little at an angle on entry.
Saved it quite well in terms of the splash.
But just check how vertical he was at the moment he hit the water.
And he wasn't quite there.
The feet were just a little split as well.
Well, the nation loves him, I think.
And an eighty-three, two, five for Tom that he's certainly on that form.
Meaning for the semis.
Andrea Chiaravini, twenty-eighth, now has a reverse three and a half somersault.
Three point three, the tariff for the Italian.
He's towards the
Just not as tight, not as convincing, not taking up as good a position for the last moment of the dive.
Some of the more experienced men.
Toes need to be pointed here, they kind of got there towards the end, but just some form errors that the judges identify here.
And he's not fully straightening for the last moment.
And 54-45 for Andrea.
He'll stay in the bottom half dozen.
Next up, it's Ugaro Parisi from Brazil.
Third Olympic Games for him.
semi-finals would represent progress but back in 29th this arm stand back double somersault two and a half twist needs to be absolutely on the money well he looked to have a good position here in the arm stand pushed away with good strength twists were okay
Not too much wrong with that dive except for the finish.
Not leaving that good impression for the judges, but 75.6.
Peter Waterfield, who is the Commonwealth Games gold medalist in Manchester, said the home crowd inspired him and he needs a bit of that from these supporters now to keep up the progress because the last dive was a belter.
He's pulled out a 90.
This is a back three and a half somersault tux, just a 3.3 tariff.
Well, again, one of those dives where the athlete saves the entry, even though they weren't quite vertical.
And with a 3.3 instead of a 3.7 difficulty, which was the case with his previous drive, he can't hope to score around 90.
He didn't get to the vertical.
Minimal splash but not optimal position.
He's still arching on his way in.
Well, he's going to give the crowd a difficult evening because he's flirting with qualification.
Eighteen, remember, we're looking for from this evening who will be back here at ten o'clock in the morning
They've got a long way through this competition at the Olympic Games, right to the end before getting underway.
And here is the standings after four of six dives.
Kubo, Sasha Klein, really impressive.
Lin Yue, German Sanchez, Galperin, the two Mexican divers.
Tom Daley up to seventh now, gradually working his way up the field.
doing a bit of a Mo Farah mainly working his way up the field.
Now this is the important cut.
David Budaya more uncomfortable than he would have liked.
Young Jimmy Connor just scrambling the right side of the line but only, well, less than three points ahead of Jankler Aguirre and Peter Waterfield is pulling up there and trying to claw back the ground he lost with those opening dives.
He's pretty much halved the deficit he had after the previous round.
He was some 18 to 20 points adrift of the cutoff and now he's only nine behind.
So, you know, he's got two dives left and can be done, that's for sure.
It is doing it the hard way though.
Unnecessary pressure, you think?
Cleb Galperin kicking us off again.
Oh dear, he's just switched off.
Well we said it's a long night, I caught one diver having a bit of a yawn in the recovery pool a moment ago.
And this is just a terrible entry, it's completely the wrong entry angle.
And a 34.65 for Galper and he doesn't score that too often.
He was ranked fifth.
So, he's got slack but I would advise doing that tomorrow if he makes the the cut successfully enough.
Lin Yue from China.
Arm stand back.
Double somersault.
Two and a half twists.
Worth three point six.
And he is in third place after four dives.
It's
from Guangdong province, five foot four, eight stone five, pretty perfect size and shape that for a diver.
And again, he's done a nice job of retrieving the dive at the end here.
The ankles lost each other at the top, but he found the water well and didn't make much of a splash.
And the judges want to give him high eights.
Just corkscrewing his way through the air and into the water.
And a ninety-one point eight.
Well, the three point seven difficulty certainly assists.
Victor Ortega.
Sixteen, right side of the line for the Colombian.
And he should stay there too.
That's a lovely dive from Ortega.
taken swimming when he was just three years of age by his parents because he was struggling with asthma and they felt the exercise would do him a lot of good.
So another example there of just how much a sporting lifestyle can help your overall health, providing you can dive off a 10 meter board of course.
And Victor Ortega, an 84-15, keeps himself very much in contention to continue.
Anton Zakharov with an arm stand back, triple somersault.
Ninth, so he's fairly comfortable.
Let's watch his pike position in this one.
Oh no, I didn't like it.
He wasn't very straight with his legs and the hands go to the faces of his little cheer squad there and he was all over the place.
The knees were bent initially, got it to a straight position, then twisted and was at less than a perfect angle coming in.
And that'll hurt.
47-25.
They'll all know that if they do progress through to tomorrow and then tomorrow evening that a poor dive is just not on if they have genuine ambitions of being in contention for the medals.
Timofey Odeychik from Belarus.
I think he's left himself too much to do.
Rank 29th coming into this one.
He controlled that dive really well, but the better guys can just give that impression for the judges with much less splash than this.
He seems to hit the water very vertically and then doesn't control what happens after it.
He's reached finals in the synchronized events at World Championship level, but again finding it harder to make an impact in the individual competition.
Here's young Hyun Joo Ri from the Democratic People's Republic of Korea, 16-year-old.
Well, I know that's a big splash, but that's actually one of his better dives in this competition for Ri, and the coach looks a little more pleased.
He's had a difficult night.
But if the sport is to progress in these countries, then they have to take the risk of bringing divers to this level of competition, getting that experience and try and build that knowledge base.
And it's experience too for the coaching staff, not just for the competitors, the whole team gains from the experience.
How to prepare your athletes for competition, what to say to them before and afterwards, that's all a learning experience for coaches as well as what the athletes go through.
all these individual athletes, not just in the pool but talk about the team behind them.
Jimmy Connor from Australia, the seventeen-year-old who is eighteenth right on the edge, reverse three and a half somersault tucked which he has to get fairly right.
Looks so young, doesn't he?
Of these vulnerable moments.
Well, a fairly nice job done with that, but as I just mentioned, he is right on the cusp.
And Jiangning Chen is his coach.
Quite a lot of Chinese coaches working with the diving program in Australia, and he's getting sevens for this.
You can see for yourself he's not got quite the entry he would have desired.
You'll have to excuse our understandable parental instincts coming in here because these are young lads and you do you are a parent and millions out there watching will be of course you've got to empathize with what these young lads are putting themselves through.
I think you'd be pretty proud of all of them if they're up there.
Martin Wolfram at 20.
A little bit more mature.
He's eighth.
Not doing too badly at all.
Back two and a half somersault.
Two and a half twists in there as well.
3.6 that one.
Didn't quite finish it off as he would have wanted.
Looked good through the air.
Got all the elements completed.
Those ankles very much together.
And again, just that very last aspect.
Judges.
It's interesting how they set them up.
They can't see each other.
They're sort of all partitioned off.
Four on one side and three on the other.
He's happy though, is Martin.
And again we must emphasize they don't get the front views, the top views, the side views because you can see them really maybe yawing or not quite getting the move right through all dimensions.
They've got less than two seconds to make the judgment call.
Jankla Aguirre, who's 19th and still fighting to stay in the competition.
With that reverse, three and a half somersault tucked.
That looked very good from here.
I think he might just be giving himself a bit of room to breathe.
If that's an expression.
If it wasn't, it is now.
Breathing room might come out better, but that was a lovely entry from Aguirre.
of good.
Yeah, eighty-five point eight helps when you're on the bubble and he knows that.
He's he's pleased.
Confidence to take into his last dive.
I'm sure we're going to see some movement on the leaderboard though.
With the sixth and final.
Alexander Bondar from Ukraine.
Twelfth
Well, when he's good, he's very good, Bondar.
Ukraine wanting to get two athletes to progress.
Eighth in the World Championships at ten meters in Shanghai last year.
Did get a little off the square, Bondar, but somehow on the way down, rescued it and
Just had that one bad dive, his third was a 57, otherwise in the 80s.
Jiho Park from Korea.
He's 31st, back two and a half somersault, one and a half twists.
Just needs to put in a nice clean dive to give himself some encouragement.
And he does that.
He's towards the bottom of the field, ranked 31st coming in.
to this fifth dive and at this point competing for pride as we often say there's something in that studies and trains at the Korea University of Physical Education in Seoul 72 his score there very consistent 7.5 right across
Victor Mini Bayev.
That view not for the queasy is it?
Back three and a half somersault piked.
Thirty-two foot ten inches above the water in Old Money.
Back three and a half somersault
Wow, he looked so good through the air.
Such a shame that he's spoiled it with that finish.
Minibaev.
Look at the position he achieves here in Pike.
Those legs are so straight.
Pulls for the water now and just over they go.
Big splash.
And that'll hurt.
Minibaev with a 48.6.
Oh, he'd like to take that back.
Or at least the last bit.
No margin for error.
Well, maybe a little bit tonight in terms of qualifying but after that you've got to get it right across the six dives if you're going to do yourself justice.
German Sanchez has been fairly close to doing that.
Fourth in the rankings to date.
This is his fifth dive.
It's a reverse three and a half
in relative terms.
He does a good job with it too.
I like him.
German Sanchez.
I think we will see him not just in the semi-final but the final.
His class spots the water, goes in with a minimum of fuss and in good position.
He's in the flyweight division remember and only forty-seven K. Seven stone six.
Eighty-four point one five.
And he's on his way.
What about Riley McCormick?
Twenty-one later this month.
The Canadian.
He is fourteenth.
Reverse
Again, just a little sloppy at the end for Riley, who can't make any big slip-ups here.
He's only a few positions inside the cut.
And again, over go the legs with this over rotation at the finish.
The timing is just so difficult to get spot on.
World Championship finalist in Shanghai last year.
So, he will have definitely set his stall out to be here tomorrow night, let alone tomorrow morning.
Now, you give him ten out of ten for unpredictability, Matthew Mitcham, defending champion and this is an arm stand back triple somersault and there is a lot of him to get up level there.
Short.
He managed to minimise the damage with the entry but he wasn't vertical and we're just gathering an impression, or at least I am, that he's not the diver he was four years ago.
He still loves being on the Olympic stage clearly with his reaction but you see he's short there.
He doesn't lack personality, it's just form he seems to lack.
Certainly it's not talent, we know that, he's proved that.
You just feel he's a bit of a natural performer if he could just get himself in the frame of mind, get himself in the final.
He's one of those guys that if he has his day, it's a good day.
He was on my plane coming over from Sydney and at the airport that people just couldn't get enough of him.
He's so recognisable within Australia.
Such a distraction for him I think at that level.
their uh shy types really wouldn't be quite right in diving it's a it's a show-off sport isn't it basically Armand Gizmovic of Norway that's his best entry so far Gizmovic first Norwegian to qualify for the Olympics remember since 1992
I think what you say, Roger, is a point worth elaborating that some of the divers say, look, our bodies are on display, we're very much on display.
You see all of us, our courage is also exposed, and in that sense, it's no place for shrinking violets.
It's a performance.
It's a show.
It's the same with the gymnasts as well.
You can see they get the dismount right and the great smile and they love the applause.
I wonder how much of the applause they hear underwater.
I'm feeling they sense it.
Francesco Delomo from Italy with a reverse three and a half somersault.
He's twenty-first, not over for him yet by any means.
He needs to get this three point three difficulty correct and get some points on the board.
Oh and that's two consecutive average dives from Delomo and and he was in contention to be in the semi-final two dives ago and it's just slipping away from him now.
32 contestants.
So it's a big field.
It's a long time between the dives, but I Remember in the three meter springboard, which is probably the most contested category They're having more than 50 divers for a world championship and that is a long long competition and a long wait between dives.
Christopher Eskilsson from Sweden.
Where's he?
23rd equal.
Oh, and whatever is going wrong with Duomo is going wrong with Eskilsson.
That's twice now that both men have had a chance to make a statement late in the competition about forcing their way into the top 18, and they've just not delivered.
This is a great shame.
They're good enough, but there's the pressure, that intangible.
You've got the platform, you've got the pool, and you've got a very short amount of time to get it right.
and it's what's between the ears then but they can sometimes be the differential.
Eric Sane from Canada's first Olympic Games are proving a tough test for him.
28th, this is a back three and a half somersault.
Canadians normally send quite a strong team with quite a high sense of ambition, so I think he'll be feeling the discomfort here back in 28th position before these scores are added in.
They've got such a great tradition, haven't they, in the sport?
Look at Departee.
Alexander, one of the greats of all time, really, you can consider his longevity and success.
And they've got a couple of bronzes so far in this Olympics.
So the team will be feeling confident, but he's just not had his day, has he?
No, forty-nine-five there for Eric.
And I think he'd like it to to be over now.
Brian Nixon Lomas from Malaysia.
He's twenty-six.
He has an inward four and a half somersault.
This is a really difficult dive.
Four point one.
Ten out of ten for Ambition.
Oh, and we'll give him high marks for execution too.
The coaching staff are happy.
Could have just performed himself into the next round here.
Lomas.
He's had a little bit of inconsistency through his competition this evening, but a very difficult dive done well.
The degree of difficulty is really going to kick him up here.
Smiles all around.
He's won Commonwealth Games medals and Asian Games medals, so he's used to performing and delivering.
96.
A good score and 96 is a good score.
Boy, it can change very dramatically, can't it?
Gives you an idea of what lies ahead in this competition when it really starts to hot up over the next 24 hours.
This is Ivan Garcia in sixth place and he's got a reverse three and a half somersault tucked here.
for watching.
You might be able to hear our Spanish speaking colleagues next door loving the Mexican performances and the way Guadalajara just rolls off the tongue.
It is a beautifully named place, isn't it?
I feel like I've got to go there just because of Guadalajara.
Famous World Cup football venue it was in Mexico.
That's where it's famous name in Britain.
And Mexicans are showing that diving as well as football is one of their strong sports and they're having a good games.
And an eighty-five point eight for Ivan.
He's looking pretty secure.
Two silver and a bronze for Mexico so far in these games and he might fancy adding to that if their two divers really have a big night.
Nick McCrory.
Tenth position.
Back three and a half somersault for the
Well, it was OK.
He's had his moments tonight as well.
Needs to just be steady here and make sure he finishes it off.
Well, a top 10 diver when he's in form.
They're going to be back in less than 12 hours.
So the schedulers have put them on the spot a bit, I think.
Seven o'clock here in the UK started and it's not going to finish till after 10 o'clock and then they're back at 10 o'clock in the morning.
It's time to get home and I might need a massage.
It is a tight schedule, isn't it?
I looked at it and thought it's demanding on a number of people.
not worry about us but you know crews and staff and and of course the athletes.
That's Deira.
He was in 22nd position with a reverse three and a half somersault there.
He'll be wanting to have a difficult 12 hours.
Lots of eights coming in.
He's really got a few places to make up though.
His fifth and sixth dives, 79.2.
18th with some to come though with this fifth dive series.
Sebastian Villa now, twenty-year-old Colombian.
Twenty-third his ranking back three and a half somersault which he delivers very quickly.
He does and delivers well.
Not much of a splash from the guy.
He's only uh some fifty-four kilos uh than sixty-four centimeters.
So, not a lot of him.
good entry.
Don't think he's got a huge amount of experience at this level of competition, World Championship or Olympic, where it's a different world.
The divers must find some of the performances of the top competitors intimidating almost.
Not David Baudia who's up next though.
And again you're getting a look at the good camaraderie down on the pool deck.
So opposition coaches give some congratulations.
The athletes walking past.
Back three and a half somersault for David Budaya who is 17th and just living on the edge a bit.
So there's little imperfections we're seeing from those below the top five.
A wonderful pike position.
Stretches, reaches, splashes.
So sevens.
Seven and a halfs.
The eight will be discarded.
And an 81.
Difficulty helping them along there with a 3.6 tariff.
He's going to get you bowed out.
Leading the pack here for the eighteen-year-old.
How does he do it?
He bounced along that board before he got it like it's a springboard almost.
Yes, it's a real looping approach if you like.
It's just very light on his feet.
Easy through the air.
But making a few headlines.
And Choubo is confirming his standing here with a 99.9.
As we said, he comes from a very poor background and he knows that Olympic success will transform not only his life but that of his family as well.
This is Sasha Klein who's doing very well, second place.
Reverse three and a half somersault there.
So he's trying to split the two Chinese champions, Chu and Lin.
There's some 20 points difference between Chu and Lin.
or 66 to 445.
Let's see if Sasha Klein can force his way in there.
Very solid dive.
and an eighty-nine one.
Twenty-six.
This really could see him at his absolute peak.
Just staying in the zone.
I think they call that.
In his own world there, isn't he, Lynn?
A climb just one point behind Lynn.
Just couldn't sneak in ahead of him but an eighty-nine.
Very nice dive.
Great result.
Vadim Kaptur from Belarus.
Twenty-five year old from Minsk.
Fifteenth.
Back three and a half
Four World Championships, six European Championships.
Got the experience, has he got the points to keep it going?
Hasn't got the finish there.
I'm afraid they're not cheering that dive, they're cheering the next competitor.
3.3 was the tariff there.
They give us the names of the athletes and some of the sheets we have.
They usually put the last name first.
We don't see Thomas Daly.
It's presented to me as Daly Thomas.
I nearly want to say Daly Thompson.
But they're quite different sports and quite different bills.
But maybe a taste of the same success from the great decathlete across to Thomas Daly.
both have tremendous popularity Tom Daly 18 years of age and getting better as the competition progresses back three and a half somersault three point six the tariff and he is seventh after a shaky start oh my goodness by his standards that's a terrible ending to that dive three point six degree of difficulty but oh I think he's embarrassed to come up
He's putting this home support right through the mincer here, isn't he?
Won't do the confidence of his teammate Peter Waterfield any good.
He's got to come up with two very good dives to make it to the semi.
And the 39.6 sees him tumble to 16th.
Oh, this is a diver who set new British record points totals this year.
We're not seeing it this evening.
Andrea Ciarabini now from Italy, forward three and a half somersault.
and he's just ready diving for personal pride back in 30th.
He's one of those young divers who will gain enormously from the opportunity to compete here but it's not possible with his scores now to progress to the semi.
Just 17 years of age.
We must emphasize again.
Hugo Parisi and then Waterfield.
That'll complete the fifth dives.
Parisi is 28.
This is a reverse three and a half somersault tucked.
He's in 27th position, the Brazilian.
Nice dive.
I just wonder at 28 whether he would be tempted to just hang on for Rio in four years time.
He'd be in his 30s.
I mean it's possible.
Stay injury free.
This is one of his better ones.
Fairly good vertical position for the entry from Hugo Parisi.
Toes have got a good grip on the end of the platform there.
Acting like hands really with the grip.
A little bit of excitement at the end of every series of dives, because the last man up is the very popular Brit, Peter Waterfield.
And he, like Tom Daley, is making sure his many supporters have an anxious night.
He too has been pulling his way up the field, but he too cannot afford to blow another dive.
Reverse three and a half somersault, he's in 20th position and diving to make the cut.
Bit of a splash there, wasn't there?
That's not what he needed.
It should have been tidier than that to just claw back a few more points and take some more pressure off.
His fourth dive was so good, he really did something about his position.
But that splash means he can only get sixes and six and a halfs.
Amazing range of dives there between four and a half and seven.
That's some inconsistency there.
I know those two scores come out but you don't want to be seeing four and a half and seven as a range.
They've got to be closer than that.
Well, he's piled all the pressure on himself for the last dive, but it's China one and two.
Sascha Klein, Germany and the two Mexican divers and Germany having a good, good evening.
Martin Wolfram there up into sixth.
Matthew Mitchum tenth.
We should at least see him again.
David Budair as well.
Other big names.
Gleb Galperin has slipped away a bit like Tom Daly.
Gleb Galperin had a very good start.
Tom Daly, that disastrous dive but still in with a chance.
There's the cut just behind James Connor hanging on by his fingertips.
Vadim Kaptur and Brian Lomas.
The were the two
program you've organized and just where you've put your bigger tariff dives can really make the big difference, can't it?
Whether you've saved it for the end or put them in mid-competition.
Proud have stayed with it commendably all the way through the competition.
Got a feeling this is very much the appetizer for the big one when it starts tomorrow and into tomorrow night.
Waterfield in twenty-third position.
That's tough to come back from.
Galperin started off like a train but come a little bit off the rails in the latter stages.
So he want to make sure he finishes strongly with this back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist with a three point six tariff.
Yes, just to extend the analogy a bit further, it's a train that's running out of steam, I think.
That entry angle was seriously short of vertical.
He's got great dives in him, but he needs six back-to-back to challenge the top few.
He's got a very distinguished career behind him but again, those eight operations on his back and knee.
He missed two years of diving.
Done brilliantly to get back but maybe he's just finding it a bit tougher to try and string a whole series of dives together.
Eighty-one points there with seven and a halves.
The marks that count.
He's got an anxious half hour just to
Back at the top of the ranking or second top Lin Yue has beaten Xu the world champion at the national trials in May so he's not come here for silver but that is for tomorrow of course.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
He's some 21 points behind his teammate.
The finish of this dive not quite perfect, but very tidy through the air.
There are just beautiful gymnasts.
Not too much wrong with that.
He sort of collapsed into that somersault beneath the water.
There's the crossover of the ankles there.
The judges do well to see that.
86.4.
had an injury to his waist over the last year or two, which is quite unusual.
Must be running the core stomach muscles which come under such a lot of strain.
Victor Ortega from Colombia.
He's ninth.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
Just needs to keep it tidy.
If you're wondering what that tattoo is on this lower chest, it's life because that's what he embraces.
Give it everything.
And it's part of his sort of personal philosophy of how he approaches things.
It's a very individual sport that seems to attract individualists.
A lot of them, they're really strong characters with a bit of an artistic side to their nature because they like to see it as what they're doing, as being very creative.
Yes, it takes a certain type of person to want to jump off a three, a 10 metre platform.
Anton Zakharov from the Ukraine.
He's 14th.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Very tidy.
What's his consistency been like over the evening?
Zakharov coming in at 14th before this dive and he's had a near disastrous 47.25 as his fifth dive but 70s, 80s and now 86.4.
He's got away with that nightmare fifth dive hasn't he really?
There'll be some competitors here who'd like to have the option of dropping their worst dive, call it their mulligan.
Not possible.
Timofey Odeychik from Belarus down in 29th.
Reverse three and a half somersault is his farewell dive.
He's just not able to control his entries
makes a big splash dive after dive that's not even with a poor position so he's got to learn how that's done there's a couple of tricks that happen under the water he hasn't mastered after finishing 10th in the world championships last year I think he's going to get into bed tonight and think that he's not really done himself justice
Kyung Joo Ri from Democratic People's Republic of Korea, the 16-year-old.
Almost on work experience here, really.
Down in 32nd place.
Oh, he's finished the competition well.
His fifth dive was one of his best and his last clearly his best.
You want to see them leave feeling good about themselves.
We mentioned how much on display they are and when you're this age and your ego is a fragile thing.
It's the other noticeable aspect of these Olympics that it's the the highest level of competition but away from that top there is a great feeling of support from the crowds to to competitors who are young or trying to make their mark.
This is Jimmy Connor here at seventeen.
He's right on the bubble at eighteenth.
There'll be a lot of people in Australia, family and friends got their fingers crossed for this next dive.
See if he can make it through.
Back two and a half
Oh, he's done a fairly decent job of it too.
So he's going to have to be beaten.
He hasn't played himself out of contention.
He's put in a good dive and now the cards let them fall how they may.
And this is what you want to see.
Everyone putting together a good competition so that if you get beaten by a better diver, that's OK, but rather than you not giving of your best.
I think it's the divers who've cut out the disasters who will feel that at least they've put on some sort of a show.
67.2 we're not with a high tariff there so he's not been able to get into the 70s but it may be enough.
Depends on those around him how they respond.
Martin Wolfram from Germany's had a good evening up in sixth.
Forward four and a half somersault.
Powerful dive that.
3.7 the tariff.
Well he's been tidy all evening and he's kept it going to the last.
And something in the 90s here.
Really committed himself to that dive along the platform, didn't he?
He's happy and justifiably.
He's improved.
He had two in the seventies, then two dives in the eighties, three in fact, and then one in the nineties.
So he's one to watch.
Aguila 12th, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist for the Cuban age 22 in his second Olympic Games.
Well, that's a busy dive, isn't it?
There's a lot going on right there.
Three point six degree of difficulty.
Two and a half twists, two and a half somersaults.
It's just a blur of limbs and torso spinning.
Well, after he reached the semifinal in Beijing, he will be looking for at least that four years on.
Reminder is an amazing thing that it can make the body do that so quickly.
Eighty-four point six Aguirre.
Alexander Bondar who came eighth in the Syncro competition.
Remember the eighteen-year-old Ukrainian back two and a half somersault two and a half twist to complete his program and he is in seventh place.
Another solid effort.
He's had up to here, he's had four good dives and one poor one and that's closer to good than poor.
I think he'll have his sights set on being here tomorrow night, not just tomorrow morning.
Yes, not quite as clean perhaps as the Chinese with his leg form and the pike position he briefly gets into here.
Those knees were bent.
81 though.
He's at three point six tariff.
And he's done enough, I'm sure.
Jiho Park from Korea, Busan.
Twenty-eighth arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twists.
And he's
It was a real effort getting away from the platform, wasn't it?
There's a little microphone up there to catch any noises coming from the divers.
Yeah, just another man gathering experience, you feel.
The arm strength needed to get some height from that, not just fall away into the dive, just collapse into it.
The top exponents there really pushing, pumping themselves away from the platform.
Yes, he's not the most powerfully built of the divers we have here.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Now he's in seventeenth place with not much room to spare.
Eighteen, remember, is the cutoff point.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Well, if he was in trouble before, he's not now.
Fourth at the Worlds last year in Shanghai, you look at that and realize that he's got something more in him.
And there it is.
He's delivered and he'll be fine because he's got the good score coming here.
current European silver medalist, so he's a man with expectations to succeed and perform.
When you see a dive like that, you wonder what was he doing, 17th with one dive to come.
That doesn't help James Connor, who's the man on the cusp, if you like, as Minnibaev sort of blows him away.
He was already in front of him, but only just.
German Sanchez from Mexico in fourth place.
Forward four and a half somersault to finish up with and he's put down an encouraging marker for Mexico.
A little sloppy from him.
He wanted to put himself in danger though.
He's too high up the rankings to fall out of the top 18.
But this one was overdone.
That extra fourth rotation takes a little bit of pulling out of and they're running out of space to do it.
Sixty-six point six.
Secret Handshake exchanged and on we go.
Riley McCormick from Canada, 13th place, back three and a half somersault.
Didn't make the final in Beijing, he was 16th.
And another man who I think is now safe.
Certainly couldn't afford a major mistake sitting 13th, but with this dive, we can count him in.
Nicely executed.
Reaches for the water.
Maybe not quite vertical, but he's got that skill of minimising the splash.
I'll be all right.
86.4.
Yeah, a little sigh of relief there.
I'm sure he must have known in his heart he had it covered, but you're still in the hands of the judges, aren't you?
Matthew Mitchum, defending champion.
10th place after five dives, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists.
What is the Australian going to come up with this time?
Oh, one of his better ones.
And I think we've just got another locked into the top 18.
He looked less than his best early in the competition, but he's starting to find form.
He might tell us later that he always had it under control.
and he looks safely through the Beijing champ I think he is a sort of highly experienced competitor who knows that he's just got to get himself through this you know and it's not being won tonight he's um that's been a tad unpredictable 84.6 though we'll see him safely across the line and into morning competition
Amund from Norway down in twenty-four finishes with it in with three and a half somersault tucked.
Very nice.
He's had a couple of good dives and a few not really Olympic class but
and he's pulling some good scores for it too.
Maybe just came in a little nervous at 21 and so pretty good on the one meter springboard so he's got a range of skills across the disciplines and
Up now with Francesco De Luomo from Italy.
Arm stand forward double somersault with one twist.
Which is only worth 3.1.
He's in 26th place, just getting himself up into that position.
No, it's such a disappointing thing because his first three dives were so good and now, pardon the obvious pun, he's plummeted out of contention with just a drop-off in form that maybe comes from confidence.
The fourth dive was poor, so was the fifth, the sixth.
He had little chance by this stage.
He was almost dropping into that dive there.
The top divers have really snapped themselves still out of that arm stand position.
60.45 for Francesco.
Kristoffer Eskilsson from Sweden.
He's 27th.
Forward four and a half somersault to end.
Didn't quite reach that desired position for the entry.
That's such a lot of somersaults to get through.
Four and a half of them.
Three points.
It's his most difficult dive.
He saves it not illogically for last.
But I just wonder too if there isn't an argument for putting them in a little earlier when you know the competition is going to go for three hours plus.
rather than trying to rely on keeping your concentration and form and confidence going over what amounts to a three-hour competition.
Eric Sane from Canada, down in thirtieth position.
Not had the best of nights.
Reverse three and a half
not a lot of elevation off the platform is to rip through these somersaults but does it does a good job really by the time he reaches the water he's got it under control and all that camera angle is just frightening isn't it when you see how close the head goes
Maybe it's a bit like the view from the passenger seat sometimes when it's it looks worse from there than it does when you're the actual driver but you shudder at the thought if they just catch themselves.
We wouldn't be the first at all but no wonder they get injured.
Brian Lomas.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half
Maybe.
Oh this is what this is one for the calculator and the judges it and we'll wait for the tabulation to be done at the end but he I think he's improved his position here a little.
That's a good dive from Brian.
So four eights, two of them rejected, but eights and a seven and a half and an 84.6 is that that's a much bigger score than James Connor got for his last dive.
He has dived in World Championship finals so he will have come in here hoping Ivan Garcia of Mexico fifth ranked forward two and a half somersault three twists and he's had an encouraging evening.
Didn't need his dive in this last series to be anything too special, and frankly it wasn't, but he's got a lot of room to play with.
The Synchro Silver Medalist, remember?
He might be one of those divers who's looking to continue to improve throughout the competition and maybe mount a medal challenge if others don't deliver of their best.
A high tariff there helping Boostery score to 79.8.
Now Nick McCrory, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists.
In eighth, pretty comfortable.
3.6 the tariff.
We'll just want to sign off nice and clean and then head off for a night's rest.
Yeah, that'll give him some confidence.
No nightmares with his last dive.
He's a world top 10 diver, sixth at the world's last year.
Clean, nice entry.
Tall man at 180 centimetres or 5'11".
So there's a bit more of him to get around and a bit more of him to make a splash, but he's got it all under control.
Job done in general terms tonight for Nick.
Good job, as American coaches like to say, I think.
Good job.
He's 21st, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists, 3.6.
Needs to pull out a bit of a blinder here.
Which he does.
Giving himself an outside chance here.
Jose Guerra from Santiago de Cuba.
The veteran in the field at 33.
He's competed in five world championships.
A couple of eight and a halfs and a nine are going to count here for a big last effort of ninety-three point six.
And he's up to sixteenth.
Not bad for a thirty-three year old.
22nd position finishes with a reverse three and a half somersault.
He needs some really strong marks here.
Pulls it around.
And that effort of straightening up the left in bent at the hips a little is too flexible.
And so competes on one meter and three meter springboard.
Up now to David Budaya, the Syncro bronze medalist from what must seem like a long time ago, the beginning of last week.
He's eleventh.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists to complete his evening's work.
There's such a range of body types competing in this platform event.
He's a big strong man, powerful shoulders, the shoulders of a gymnast.
That's a splash he won't be pleased he didn't see.
He did start as a gymnast actually.
He broke a bone in his foot and felt that it was just a bit burned out by gymnastics.
So decided diving off 10 meters was a more comfortable way to go.
Takes all sorts.
It's a very demanding sport to stick with.
David Badiah's 17th position and things looking shaky for James Connor.
Now we'll be able to bring you the final 18 shortly.
Chubo, the 19 year old, the favourite from China.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
I was just looking at this, he didn't actually need to do that last dive.
So far ahead, without doing it, he would have qualified in the top 10.
Great thrust away from the platform, into his twists.
And again, what an entry.
in this form he looks untouchable his arm movements through that he's in one position for the twist then down back behind to hold up the pike and then out so much going on as you've said before in so many different parts of his body and a ninety-seven two he's at two ninety-nines Sasha Klein from Germany
third after five dives back two and a half somersault two and a half twists again looking to leave on a high wasn't his best dive be very tempting to switch off when you're in his position he's so firmly entrenched in the top getting late local time bit after 10 in the evening
Three hours of competition, tough on divers.
A thought for the judges as well, that's a lot of concentration going on.
My real sympathy though is with the competitors because it's not easy to finish a competition, go back to the village and get yourself to sleep within a couple of hours of competing because you're pumped.
They've got to refuel, they'll need to take the right things on board and
Get some rest.
I think the scheduling's crazy.
I'm just amazed about the short turnaround.
Pardim Kaptur from Belarus, 19th just on the outside looking in, reverse three and a half somersault to save it.
I mean, if we finish work at five o'clock in the afternoon, we're not expected to be back at work at five in the morning.
And that's the ask here.
Now, Kaptur finishes his evening's work.
Now, Tom Daly is up next.
That's why you can hear the crowds.
Let's just confirm Kaptur's mark.
64.35 and he can have a bit of a lie-in tomorrow.
And it's not like they just turn up at 10 o'clock in the morning either.
They're here early to warm up.
Here's a big moment though.
Massive cheer.
Can't afford to have another disaster.
16th after round five and really we've had all sorts so far.
You can hear the, feel the crowd just willing one more strong dive from their local hero.
There you go, well maybe I called it a bit early because he's flipped the feet over but the crowd certainly had their say.
He's got just a bit to play with, with the top 18 going through and he was sitting 16.
They are willing him on.
He's everybody's favourite son.
And they would all just love him to do well.
It really is a supportive sound, I feel, not just a pressure, if he can see it like that.
He's going to make it.
He's through.
He's ranked 15th and there's three to come and we know a couple of them are no chance.
So he is into the semi-final.
Thomas Daly.
maybe not quite the way he was looking.
That will of course affect his dive position tomorrow in the batting order.
Andrea Chiarabini who's pretty out of it.
Make two and a half somersault, one and a half twists to end up what's not been his greatest night.
But at 17, a key learning experience in his sporting career.
And he has finished off nicely here.
Roger, this is one of his better dives.
Pressures off and that sometimes has a bit to do with it when you know you can't progress.
The weight comes off the shoulders.
Nicely done.
75.2.
So, he's got it in him.
He'll be back.
He sticks at it and he keeps the appetite.
And fancies a trip to Rio.
And who wouldn't?
Hugo Parisi.
Who knows all about
25th.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
And again, it has to bend at the hips and that spoils the entry and creates that big splash.
So Parisi not quite there, finishing towards the bottom of the field.
some kind of a miracle needed with a last dive for our last man.
Making sure the competition comes to a dramatic conclusion.
Peter Warfield of Great Britain, massive cheer, but he has got work to do.
23rd
he's got an olympic silver medal remember in synchro and he needs to draw and all that experience and all that talent now to be back tomorrow morning big moment for a local lad born just down the road oh just a little short a punch of the water underneath the surface and
I don't know if it's enough.
He needs around 440 in total.
He's been such a storming influence in British diving for more than a decade.
Competing at World Championships right back in 1997.
but this may well prove a trip too far and 23rd is his ranking he couldn't pull the enormous score that he needed and so Budaya is the last man in oh that would have been quite a sensation if he'd missed there's the uh the ranking the two Chinese divers setting the standard Sasha Klein and Martin Wolfram a good night for Germany and for Mexico
Alexander Bondor, Nick McCrory from Ukraine and the United States respectively, Matthew Mitcham, more to come from him.
Anton Zakharov, Victor Minibaev, Tom Daly the local hero in fifteenth, Gleb Galperin fading rather but showing he's got ability.
These marks will not count tomorrow.
They start again from scratch.
David Bouda, Jose Guerra and Brian Lomas and Jimmy Connor, the two most disappointed men really.
They just missed the cut.
They are on standby I think but these divers can just put it down to a massive Olympic experience.
A long night of competition here but I've got a feeling overall Steve that it is an appetiser and the top men, although we've seen some outstanding performances at the top end, are really just warming up and getting into their stride.
I just felt that Choubo didn't have to dive as well as he did but he's in doing so he's made a statement he's summed 31 points clear of Ligneux and then back to Klein so 563 for Choubo go back to third 525 and that is a massive amount to make up and there were no weaknesses in Choubo's performance so he looks good for the gold and for China to continue their dominance
he has been beaten before tubo tom daly famously did it in 2009 when the pressure did get to him but he's a more experienced diver now and it is that ability to just churn out these top top quality dives he
He's not yet dazzled but I don't think he's been under the pressure to really do everything he can do.
He knows he's got plenty spare but a great appetizer.
This is a great event and we're looking forward to just seeing more great dives.
We don't care who they come from because we're being richly entertained here at the Aquatic Centre.
and it's dramatic stuff off the platform and the wonderful skills and courage that we're observing and we're looking forward to more of it.
I think the divers will go away.
Some with encouragement, some knowing they've got something to learn from it.
Some tonight knowing that after all that build up and all that work, it's been a bitterly disappointing evening for them.
But at the top end though, we really have seen some quality.
Chubo is a sight to behold when he's in top form.
and still got a job to do tomorrow, twice over and we're looking forward to bringing that to you from the aquatic setting.
A very difficult night ahead then for 18 divers to get their rest, get themselves mentally prepared and be back at 10 o'clock tomorrow morning
you.
Our results, defense, gold medalist.